Stop now.
不准动
Tell me where it is.
告诉我东西在哪里?
You and your brethren possess what is not rightfully yours.
你和你的弟兄们 拥有一件不属于你们的东西
I don't know what you are talking about.
我不知道你在说什么
Is it a secret you will die for?
你宁死都要保守这秘密吗?
- Please. - As you wish.
- 求求你 - 你这是自找死路
Wait!
慢着
My God, forgive me.
主啊 原谅我
In the sacristy...
圣许毕斯教堂
the church of Saint-Sulpice, is the Rose Line.
圣器收藏室有一条玫瑰线
Beneath the Rose.
东西就在玫瑰标志下方
Thank you.
谢谢你
(《神圣女性的符号》 罗柏兰登著)
Symbols are a language that can help us understand our past.
符号是帮我们了解过去的语言
As the saying goes, a picture says a thousand words...
俗语说的好 一幅图画胜过千言万语
but which words?
但是它说出什么话?
Interpret for me, please, this symbol. First thing that comes to mind.
请说出这个符号代表什么 你们想到的第一个念头
- Hatred, racism. - Ku Klux Klan.
- 仇恨 种族歧视 - 三K党
Yes, yes, interesting. But they would disagree with you in Spain.
是的 很有趣 但是西班牙人不能苟同
There, they are robes worn by priests.
这是西班牙神父穿的长袍
Now this symbol. Anyone?
那这个符号呢?
Evil.
恶魔
In English, please.
请说英文
Devil's pitchfork.
魔鬼的长柄叉
Poor, poor Poseidon.
可怜的海神
That is his trident. A symbol of power to millions of the ancients.
这是他的三叉戟 对古代人来说是力量的象征
Now this symbol.
这个符号呢?
- Madonna and child. - Faith. Christianity.
- 圣母与圣婴 - 信仰 基督教
No. No, it's the pagan god Horus and his mother, Isis...
不对 这是异教神只何露斯 以及他的母亲伊西丝
centuries before the birth of Christ.
比耶稣诞生还要早几百年
Understanding our past determines actively...
研究过去的历史能够帮助我们...
our ability to understand the present.
了解现今的世界
So how do we sift truth from belief?
我们该如何从信仰中厘清真理?
How do we write our own histories, personally or culturally...
又该如何记载我们的历史 不管是个人或是文化的历史
and thereby define ourselves?
进而确认人类的定位?
How do we penetrate years, centuries, of historical distortion...
我们该如何从扭曲的历史当中
to find original truth?
找出当初的真相?
Tonight, this will be our quest.
今晚这将是我们的任务
I still think that his whole take on phi was a little far-fetched.
我还是认为他对黄金分割率的 看法有点牵强
I don't think so. I think that the golden ratio is everywhere in nature.
我不觉得 我认为黄金分割率 在自然中俯拾即是
Sure, I can do that.
当然 我办得到
My son is a student of yours at Harvard.
我儿子是你在哈佛大学的学生
- Michael Culp? He adores you. - Oh, yeah.
- 迈可柯普呀 他很崇拜你 - 喔 是啊
He says you're the best teacher he's ever had.
他说你是他最棒的教授
Ms. Culp, I think I already gave Michael an A-minus.
柯太太 我已经给他甲下了
He told me. Thank you.
他跟我说过了 谢谢你
Mr. Langdon?
兰登先生?
Hi.
嗨
Bonjour, professor.
你好 教授
I'm Lieutenant Collet from DCPJ. A kind of French FBI.
我是刑事警察局总部科列分队长 算是法国的联邦调查局
Will you take a look at this photo, please?
请你看一下这张照片
My police chief, Capitaine Fache, had hoped...
我的长官法舍队长...
considering your expertise and the markings on the body...
希望借重你的专业知识
you might assist us.
解释他身上的符号
Will you excuse me a moment?
请恕我失陪
I was supposed to have drinks with him.
我本来约好傍晚要和他喝酒的
Yes, we know.
我们知道
We found your name in his daily planner.
他的日志本上有你的名字
He never showed. I waited for over an hour.
他爽约了 我等了一个多钟头
Why would someone do this to him?
怎么会有人对他做这种事?
Oh, you misunderstand, professor.
你误解了 教授
He was shot, yes.
他是被人用枪射死的
But what you see in the photograph...
但是他在这张照片上的样子
Monsieur Sauniere did to himself.
是索尼耶赫自己弄出来的
Teacher, all four are dead.
老师 四个人都死了
The Senechaux and the Grand Master himself.
三名大长老和盟主本人
Then I assume you have the location.
我猜你应该问出地点了
Confirmed by all.
四个人的说法都一致
Independently.
我各别逼问出来的
I had feared the Priory's penchant for secrecy might prevail.
我本来还怕锡安会员会宁死不屈
The prospect of death is strong motivation.
他们死到临头还是不敢不说
It is here.
东西在这里
In Paris, Teacher.
就在巴黎 老师
It hides beneath the Rose in Saint-Sulpice.
藏在圣许毕斯教堂玫瑰标志下方
You will go forth, Silas.
你要立刻出发 西拉
I chastise my body.
我严格的对付自己的身体
Capitaine Fache is waiting for you.
法舍队长在等你
Okay.
好吧
- Mr. Langdon. - Yes.
- 兰登先生 - 是的
I'm Captain Bezu Fache.
我是伯居法舍队长
You like our pyramid?
你喜欢我们的金字塔吗?
It's magnificent.
非常壮观
A scar on the face of Paris.
是巴黎脸上的一道疤
After me, please.
请跟我来
It's the pairing of those two pyramids.
这是倒置金字塔
It's unique.
非常特别
The two are geometric echoes.
两座金字塔相互对应
Fascinating.
有意思
I'm not sure how much help I'm gonna be here this evening.
我不确定能帮上什么忙
How well did you know the curator?
你和馆长很熟吗?
Not at all. We met only once.
不 我们只见过一次面
We were on a...
我们曾在...
On a panel together.
曾一起参与学术讨论会
Something is funny?
是什么东西好笑?
We didn't agree on much.
我们意见相左甚大
Frankly, I was surprised when he contacted me.
他跟我联络时我还吓了一跳
Could we take the stairs?
我们能不能走楼梯?
So Sauniere requested tonight's meeting.
索尼耶赫要求今晚和你碰面?
Yes.
没错
How? Did he call you?
他打电话给你吗?
E-mail. He heard I was in Paris.
电子邮件 他听说我在巴黎
Had something to discuss.
有一些事情想和我讨论
What?
讨论什么?
You seem uncomfortable.
你看起来... 很紧张
- Are any of those real? - Of course not.
- 这里面有真品吗? - 当然没有
So you know something of security procedures.
所以你懂安全程序的事
Well, I know video surveillance in a museum this size is cost-prohibitive.
我知道这么大的美术馆 因预算限制 无法全部使用监控系统
Most now rely on containment.
大部份美术馆以困住歹徒为要
Yes, forget about keeping the criminals out.
对 别想防止他们入侵了
Now we keep them in.
我们只管困住他们
The Grand Gallery. This is where you found the body.
大陈列馆 你们在这里发现尸体
How would you know that?
你怎么知道?
I recognize the parquet floor from the Polaroid. It's unmistakable.
我认得照片上的镶木地板 绝对不会有错
Dear God.
天啊
Let's cover the talking points again, Your Eminence.
让我们讨论如何回答尖锐的问题
Many call Opus Dei a brainwashing cult.
很多人说主业会是洗脑教派
Others, an ultraconservative Christian secret society.
或是极端保守基督教秘密社团
- We are a simple Catholic church. - Simple?
- 我们是个朴素的天主教教堂 - 朴素?
With a brand-new $47-million headquarters in Manhattan.
你们在曼哈顿有 斥资四千七百万的总部
Our followers are generous, should we apologize for that?
我们的信徒十分慷慨 我们难道要为此道歉吗?
Perhaps a less defensive tack, Your Eminence.
也许不该这么回答 主教大人
The press continue to be harsh with us.
记者一向对我们严厉批评
We are not Cafeteria Catholics.
我们不是马马虎虎的天主教徒
We don't pick and choose which rules to follow.
天主教有一定的教规
We follow doctrine. Rigorously.
我们必须严格遵守
Does doctrine necessarily include vows of chastity, tithing...
教规一定要包括发誓守贞 什一税以及透过...
and atonement for sins through self-flagellation and the cilice?
自我鞭笞和苦修带赎罪吗?
Many of our followers are married. Many of them have families.
有很多主业会会员已婚 也有自己的家庭
Only a small proportion choose to live ascetically...
只有少数人选择苦行的生活
in the cloisters of our residential halls.
在我们的修道院宿舍里
But we are all united in God's work around the world.
但同样的神意使命让我们不论身在何处 团结一致
Surely that is an admirable way to lead one's life.
那当然是种高尚的生活方式
Why are some media referring to Opus Dei as "God's mafia"?
为何有媒体称主业会是"上帝的黑手党"?
Obviously, some people fear what they don't understand.
有些人对不了解的事物感到害怕
And because the war finally draws to a close.
也因为战争终于落幕了
- Bishop, we need to stay on message. - That will be all, Michael, thank you.
- 主教 请说重点... - 今天就到此为止 谢谢你
Aringarosa.
我是艾林葛若萨
Silas has succeeded. The legend is true.
西拉完成任务 传说是真的
It hides beneath the Rose.
就藏在玫瑰标志下方
My part of our bargain is nearly fulfilled.
我这一边的任务就快完成了
I meet the council in an hour.
再过一小时我就要去开会
I will have your money tonight, Teacher.
我今晚会拿到你的钱 老师
The Vitruvian Man.
维特鲁威人
It's one of Leonardo da Vinci's most famous sketches.
是达芬奇最有名的素描
And the star on his skin?
他身上的星形图案是什么?
A pentacle.
五芒星
And its meaning?
它有什么涵义?
The pentacle is ancient.
这五芒星的历史悠久
Symbols carry different meanings in different settings.
符号在不同场合有不同的意义
This symbol, professor. This setting.
我要这个符号 在这里的意义
The pentacle is a pagan religious icon.
五芒星是异教的宗教符号
Devil worship.
魔鬼崇拜
No. No, no, no. The pentacle before that.
不 不是... 这是更早的五芒星
This is a symbol for Venus.
这是维纳斯女神的象征符号
It represents the female half of all things.
代表万物女性的那一半
It's a concept called "the divine goddess" by religious historians.
这是宗教历史学家称做"神圣女性的符号"的概念
You are telling me that Sauniere's last act on earth...
你是说索尼耶赫临死之前
was to draw a goddess symbol on his chest? Why?
在他胸口划了一个女神符号? 为什么?
Captain Fache, obviously I can't tell you why.
法舍队长 我也不知道
I can tell you he, as well as anyone, knows the meaning of this symbol...
我只能说他很清楚这符号的意思
and it has nothing to do with worshiping the devil.
这跟魔鬼崇拜毫无关系
- Is that so? - Yes.
- 是吗? - 是的
Then...
那么...
what do you make of this?
这又代表什么?
"O, Draconian devil. Oh, lame saint."
"啊 严峻的魔鬼 啊 跛足的圣人"
It's a phrase. Doesn't mean anything, not to me.
只是一句话 没什么涵义
What would you do if you had such limited time to send a message?
你在临死前会写下什么讯息?
Well, I suppose I'd try to identify my killer.
我猜我会写出杀人凶手的名字
Precisely.
一点也没错
So, professor...
教授...
Officer Neveu.
纳佛探员
Please, pardon the interruption.
抱歉打扰了
This is not the time.
你来的不是时候
I received the crime-scene jpegs at headquarters...
我在总部收到犯罪现场的影像档
and I've deciphered the code.
我破解了密码
It's a Fibonacci sequence.
这是斐波那契数列
That's the code Sauniere left on the floor.
索尼耶赫在地板上留下的数字
Headquarters sent me to explain, captain.
总部派我来解释这件事
It is the Fibonacci sequence.
的确是斐波那契数列
The numbers are out of order.
这些数字排序错误
But before that, I have an urgent message for Professor Langdon.
我有一个紧急口信要给兰登教授
Right?
就是您吗?
Pardon me?
什么?
I'm Sophie Neveu, French police, Cryptology.
我是苏菲纳佛 法国刑事警察局解码科
Your embassy called Division.
美国大使馆打给总部
I'm sorry, monsieur, they said it was a matter of life and death.
抱歉 他们说这件事攸关生死
This is the number of your embassy's messaging service.
这是大使馆留言服务台的电话号码
Well, thank you.
谢谢你
Hello, you've reached the home of Sophie Neveu.
你好 这是苏菲纳佛家
Miss Neveu? This...
纳佛小姐 这...
No. That's the right number.
电话号码没有错
You have to dial an access code to pick up your messages.
你得按下密码才能听到留言
But I'm getting...
可是我...
It's a three-digit code. It's on the paper I gave you.
就是那张纸上的三位数号码
Professor Langdon, do not react to this message.
兰登教授 请你保持冷静
You must follow my directions very closely and, above all...
仔细依照我的指示去做
reveal nothing to Captain Fache.
千万不要向法舍透露任何事
You are in grave danger.
你的情况非常危险
Church of Saint-Sulpice.
圣许毕斯教堂
Good evening, Sister.
你好 修女
I need you to show someone our church tonight.
我要你今晚带一个人参观教堂
Of course, Father.
是的 神父
But so late?
但是时候不早了
Wouldn't tomorrow...?
不能等到明天... ?
This is a request from an important bishop of Opus Dei.
这是一位主业会主教的要求
It would be my pleasure.
这是我的荣幸
There's been an accident. A friend.
我有一位朋友出了意外
I have to fly home in the morning.
必须搭明天一早的班机飞回去
I see.
我明白了
Is there a restroom I could use? I just wanna splash some water on my face.
这里有洗手间吗? 我想去洗把脸
Yes.
没错
She said it is meaningless.
她说那些数字没有意义
Mathematical joke.
只是一个数学玩笑
Is it meaningless?
真的没有意义吗?
I'll take another look when I come back.
等我回来再看一次
I'm sorry. Of course.
抱歉 没问题
Do you have a message from Sauniere?
你收到索尼耶赫的讯息吗?
What are you talking about?
你在说什么?
Crazy old man.
那个老疯子
You have me confused with someone else.
你恐怕认错人了 我是来...
I was asked to come here and consult.
我被请来做谘询
No, you are sous surveillance cachee.
不 你正受到监视
Yes, and...
是的 而...
What?
什么?
Bring the suspect to the crime scene and hope he incriminates himself.
把嫌犯带到犯罪现场 希望他会证明自己有罪
Suspect?
嫌犯?
Check your jacket pocket.
检查你的外套口袋
Just look.
快点
GPS tracking dot.
卫星定位系统追踪器
Accurate within two feet anywhere on the globe.
能够准确找到任何人的位置
The agent who picked you up slipped it into your jacket...
去接你的探员偷偷塞进你的口袋
in case you tried to run.
防止你试图逃跑
We have you on a little leash, professor.
他们在严密监视你的行踪
Why would I try to run? I didn't do anything.
我什么也没做 干嘛要逃跑?
So, what do you think about the fourth line of text...
这就是你来之前
Fache wiped clean before you arrived?
法舍擦掉的第四行字
(附记: 找罗柏兰登)
He brought you here to force a confession, Professor Langdon.
他是带你来逼供的 教授
He's still in there? What's he doing?
他还在里面? 他在干嘛?
Fache isn't even looking for other suspects, okay?
法舍根本就没在找别的嫌犯
He is sure you're guilty.
他认定你就是杀人凶手
When did Sauniere contact you?
索尼耶赫几时和你联络的?
- Today? - Yes, yes.
- 今天吗? - 对
What time? What time?
几点?
At 3. Around 3. Three.
三点 三点左右
The gallery alarm was triggered at 8. You were...
画廊警铃在八点被触动 你在...
- I was giving a lecture. - At 9.
- 我当时在讲课 - 是九点时
You had the privacy light on in your hotel room until 8:30, right?
你旅馆房间的"请勿打扰"告示 八点半还亮着 没错吧?
We call Fache "the Bull." Once he starts, he doesn't stop.
法舍的绰号叫蛮牛 他不达到目的 绝不罢手
He can arrest you and detain you for months while he builds a case.
他大可以把你拘留好几个月
And by then whatever Sauniere wanted you to tell me will be useless.
到时索尼耶赫要你给我的讯息 就没用了
Stop it! Just stop!
先等一下
Who are you?
你到底是谁?
What are you talking about? Tell you what?
你在说什么? 我要告诉你什么?
Maybe who really killed him.
或许说说到底是谁杀了他
The Fibonacci sequence.
斐波那契数列
I believe Sauniere wrote it...
我相信索尼耶赫写了它
so his investigation would include cryptographers.
这样调查才能包括一位 解码者
That's quite a leap, isn't it?
这样假设很大胆
No.
不
And the letters.
那两个字母
"P.S."
P.S., postscript.
"附记"的缩写
"Princess Sophie." Yeah. Silly, I know.
其实是"苏菲公主"的缩写
But I was only a girl when I lived with him.
我小时候和他一起住
Jacques Sauniere was my grandfather.
贾克索尼耶赫是我的祖父
Apparently, it was his dying wish that we meet.
他的遗愿是让我们见面
If you help me understand why...
如果你帮我查出原因
I will get you to your embassy, where we cannot arrest you.
我就带你到大使馆寻求庇护
Fache was never gonna let me just stroll out of here, was he?
法舍不会放我走 对吧?
No.
没错
If we are to get away from here, we must find another way.
我们要另外想办法逃走
What exactly do you propose?
你有什么好办法?
Sauniere was reading his book.
索尼耶赫在看他的著作
"Blood trail."
血痕
Excuse me, captain.
队长
Crypto called. They identified the code.
解码者刚通知说解开了
Neveu told us already.
纳佛已经告诉我们了
I should have fired her on the spot, barging in like that.
她那样冒然闯进来妨碍我们工作 我应该开除她
Yes.
没错
Except they didn't send Neveu.
只是总部并没有派苏菲纳佛来
What?
什么?
Captain, look at this.
队长 请看
He jumped!
他跳楼了
Shit.
该死
He's moving again. And fast.
他又在移动 速度很快
He must be in a car.
他一定在车上
He's going south on Pont du Carrousel.
他在骑兵桥上向南移动
Bastard.
可恶
That cop will check the whole lower floor.
那个警员会搜索整个楼层
I will only take a moment.
我去看一下
Of course.
没问题
He is much older than I remember.
他比我记忆中老很多
I hadn't seen or spoken to him in a very long time.
我有好久没和他见面或联络了
He phoned my office today. Several times.
他今天打到我办公室好几次
He said it was a matter of life and death.
他说这件事攸关生死
I thought it was another trick to get back in touch.
我以为他只是找借口和我联络
It seems when he couldn't speak to me...
当在他找不到我之后
he reached out to you.
就想到要请你帮忙
Whatever he needed so badly to say...
不管他急着想说什么...
he found neither of us in time.
他都没有及时找到我俩之一
- Wait a minute. - Professor?
- 等一下 - 教授?
Come on.
不会吧
It can't be that easy.
不会那么简单吧
This is wrong. Yeah. See? This is wrong.
这是错的 瞧 完全错了
The Fibonacci numbers only make sense when they're in order.
斐波那契数列必须按照排列
These are scrambled.
这些数字却完全乱掉了
If he was trying to reach out, maybe he was doing it in code.
如果他想发出讯息 也许是用密码
Would you hold this, please?
请你拿着 好吗?
This phrase is meaningless.
这句话没有意义
Unless you assume these letters are out of order too.
除非字母排列顺序不对
An anagram.
这是变位字谜
(红衣主教)
You have eidetic memory?
你记忆力过人吗?
Not quite. But I can pretty much remember what I see.
并没有 不过我几乎是过目不忘
(神圣)
(李奥纳多)
Anagram is right.
的确是变位字谜
"O, Draconian devil. Oh, lame saint" becomes:
"严峻的魔鬼 跛足的圣人"变成...
"Leonardo da Vinci. The Mona Lisa."
李奥纳多达芬奇 蒙娜丽莎
Professor, the Mona LiSa is right over here.
蒙娜丽莎的微笑就在这儿
Look at this. He must have thrown it from the window.
你看 他一定把追踪器丢下去
Smart to hit the truck.
正好丢在卡车上面
What, you admire him now?
你很佩服他 是吗?
We're stupid. Who did we leave at the museum?
我们有够笨了 谁在罗浮宫?
Ledoux? Get him on the radio!
快用无线电通知他
Her smile is in the lower spatial frequencies.
她的微笑空间频率比较低
The horizon is significantly lower on the left than it is on the right.
左方的地平线也很明显 比右方来得低
Why?
为什么?
Well, see, she appears larger from the left than on the right.
她从左边看起来比右边大
Historically, the left was female, the right was male.
左边代表女性 右边代表男性
The sacred feminine.
神圣女性的符号
Why do you say that?
你为何这么说?
Something Sauniere said the first time we came here.
是我们第一次来时 索尼耶赫说的
There. Blood.
那里有血迹
Hey.
嘿
"So dark the con of man."
"男人骗局如此阴暗"
No. It doesn't say that.
不对 并不是这个意思
Is it another anagram? Can you break it?
这又是字谜? 你能解开吗?
Professor, hurry. Hurry!
教授 快点
Moon. Sermon. Charms.
月亮 讲道 符咒
Demons. Omens. Codes. Monks. Ranks. Rocks.
恶魔 恶兆 密码 修士 官阶 岩窟
Madonna of the Rocks.
岩窟中的圣母
Da Vinci.
达芬奇的名画
Careful. Careful.
小心 小心
This can't be this. The fleur-de-lis.
不可能 白色鸢尾花
Stay where you are!
警察 不要动
Let go of the painting...
离那幅画远一点
and put it on the ground.
把它放下
No. You put your gun down.
不 你才该放下枪
Now!
快点!
Or else I will destroy the painting.
不然我撕了这幅画
Hurry up!
快点!
Slide your gun to me.
把你的枪滑过来
Be careful.
小心
I never really liked this painting.
反正我没喜欢过那幅画
Run.
快跑
It was Sauniere's.
这是索尼耶赫的东西
I remember finding it once when I was a girl.
我记得小时候曾经看过
He'd promised he'd give it to me one day.
他答应有一天要给我
Have you ever heard those words before, Sophie?
你听过这句话吗?
"So dark the con of man"?
"男人骗局如此阴暗"?
No. Have you?
没有 你有吗?
When you were a child, were you aware of any secret gatherings?
你小时候看过秘密集会吗?
Anything ritualistic in nature?
或是任何神秘的仪式?
Meetings your grandfather would've wanted kept secret?
你祖父想要隐瞒的集会?
Was there ever any talk of something called the Priory of Sion?
他有没有提过锡安会?
The what? Why are you asking these things?
什么? 你为什么问这些?
The Priory of Sion is a myth.
锡安会是一个传说中的组织
One of the world's oldest and most secret societies, with leaders like...
它是世上最古老最隐密的社团 会长包括...
Sir Isaac Newton, da Vinci himself.
牛顿爵士和达芬奇
The fleur-de-lis is their crest.
白色鸢尾花是他们的徽章
They're guardians of a secret they supposedly refer to...
他们保护着一个秘密 称之为...
as "the dark con of man."
"男人阴暗的骗局"
But what secret?
到底是什么秘密呢?
The Priory of Sion protects the source of God's power on earth.
锡安会负责保护... 上帝在这世上的权力来源
I can't do this by myself.
我一个人解不开这个谜团
I'm in enough trouble as it is. That's my embassy.
我已经惹了很大的麻烦 美国大使馆在那里
Please.
求求你
Even if we could get out of this...
就算我们逃得出去...
Okay.
好吧
No, no, no. You're not gonna make it. You're not gonna make it!
不行 你过不去 绝对过不去
Well, that was...
那真是...
We won't last long in this car.
我们开这辆车跑不远的
Fache doesn't like to be eluded, even on a good day.
法舍队长就算心情好 也不会让嫌犯脱逃
We need to get out of sight.
我们得躲起来
Christ, give me strength.
主耶稣 赐给我力量
You are a ghost.
你是白色幽灵
Christ, give me strength.
主耶稣 赐给我力量
Stealing in a house of God!
你竟敢在上帝之家偷窃
You are an angel.
你真是个天使
Christ, give me strength.
主耶稣 赐给我力量
(阿拉戈)
You have powerful friends.
你有权贵显要的朋友
Bishop Aringarosa has been kind to me.
艾林葛若萨主教对我很好
I could not miss this chance to pray inside the Saint-Sulpice.
我很想在圣许毕斯教堂祷告
A pity you couldn't wait for morning.
只可惜你不能等到早上
The light is not ideal.
光线会比较明亮
Tell me, Sister, please, of the Rose Line.
修女 告诉我玫瑰线是什么
A rose line is any line that goes from the North to South Poles.
北极到南极的直线都称为玫瑰线
Set into the streets of Paris, 135 brass markers...
其中有一条线穿过巴黎街道
mark the world's first prime meridian...
成为全世界第一条子午线
which passed through this very church.
这条线就穿过这座教堂
It hides beneath the Rose.
就藏在玫瑰标志下方
I'm sorry?
你说什么?
Sister.
修女
I do not want to keep you. I will show myself out.
你不必送我 我会自己出去
I insist.
我坚持独处
May the peace of the Lord be with you.
愿天主赐给你平静
And with you.
你也一样
Gray Smart Car. Black roof.
灰色Smart汽车 黑色车顶
Corner of Denain Boulevard at the train station.
在迪奈大道转角 巴黎车站
How could you let them get away?
你让他们溜了
Why not just shoot the damn painting? Lmbecile!
你这笨蛋 怎么没朝着画直接开枪?
You should put his cigar out in your hand!
你只配让我们用你的手 捻熄雪茄
Get out of here!
快滚
They found Neveu's car abandoned at the train station.
他们在火车站找到纳佛的车
And two tickets to Brussels paid for with Langdon's credit card.
兰登刷他的信用卡 买了两张到布鲁塞尔的火车票
A decoy, I'm sure.
他们一定在故弄玄虚
All the same, send an officer to the station.
不过还是派人去火车站
Question all the taxi drivers. I'll put this on the wire.
盘问每个计程车司机 我要把消息发给国际刑警组织
Interpol? We're not sure he's guilty.
我们还不确定他是凶手
I know he's guilty. Beyond a doubt.
我百分百确定他就是凶手
Robert Langdon is guilty.
罗柏兰登是凶手
This is the Bois de Boulogne?
这里就是布洛涅森林?
We should be safe in this park for a few minutes.
我们可以在这里躲一阵子
Your police don't patrol this park.
你们警方并不巡逻这公园
(《约伯记》 三十八章十一节)
Stay here.
留在这里
Police.
我是警察
What do you want?
你想干嘛?
Fifty euros for all your stuff.
我用五十欧元买你的毒品
Go and get something to eat.
去买点东西吃吧
Did it occur to you that could be dangerous?
你没想过那样很危险吗?
No. And now we have a place to think.
没有 现在有地方可以好好想想
Any ideas, professor?
教授 想到什么吗?
You could've just handed me a piece of a UFO from Area 51.
这一切简直就像幽浮一样荒谬
"What's the next step?"
下一步是什么?
With him, it's always:
他总是问我
"Sophie, what's the next step?"
"苏菲 下一步是什么? "
Puzzles.
拼图
Codes.
密码
A treasure hunt.
寻找宝藏
To find his killer.
找到杀死他的凶手
Maybe there is something about this Priory of Sion.
也许锡安会真的存在
I hope not.
我希望不是
Any Priory story ends in bloodshed. They were butchered by the Church.
锡安会的传说以血腥收场 会员全都惨遭教会屠杀
It all started over a thousand years ago when a French king...
传说从一千年开始
conquered the holy city of Jerusalem.
一名法国国王征服圣城耶路撒冷
This crusade, one of the most massive and sweeping in history...
史上规模最庞大的十字军东征
was actually orchestrated by a secret brotherhood...
其实是由一个秘密兄弟会
the Priory of Sion...
也就是锡安会策动
and their military arm, the Knights Templar.
他们的军队被称为圣殿骑士团
But the Templars were created to protect the Holy Land.
圣殿骑士团宣称要保护圣地
That was a cover to hide their true goal, according to this myth.
其实是为了掩饰他们真正的目的 根据传说
Supposedly the invasion was to find an artifact...
这场战争是为了找到一件古物
lost since the time of Christ.
从耶稣在世时期就遗失
An artifact, it was said, the Church would kill to possess.
教会不择手段想找到这件古物
Did they find it, this buried treasure?
他们找到这件宝物吗?
Put it this way:
我就这么说吧
One day the Templars simply stopped searching.
圣殿骑士团突然停止搜寻行动
They quit the Holy Land and traveled directly to Rome.
从圣地直接前往罗马
Whether they blackmailed the papacy...
没人知道他们是不是勒索教廷
or the Church bought their silence, no one knows.
或者是教廷付钱叫他们封口
But it is a fact the papacy declared these Priory knights...
但是事实是教宗发出诏书
these Knights Templar, of limitless power.
赐予圣殿骑士团无上的权力
By the 1300s, the Templars had grown too powerful.
他们到了十四世纪势力太强大
Too threatening.
对罗马教廷造成威胁
So the Vatican issued secret orders...
于是梵蒂冈颁发秘密封令
to be opened simultaneously all across Europe.
要在全欧洲同时拆封
The Pope had declared the Knights Templar Satan worshipers...
教宗宣称圣殿骑士团崇拜撒旦
and said God had charged him with cleansing the earth of these heretics.
并奉天主之命铲除这些异教徒
The plan went off like clockwork.
他的计划顺利完成
The Templars were all but exterminated.
圣殿骑士团几乎全军覆没
The date was October 13th, 1307. A Friday.
那天是一三零七年十月十三日 星期五
Friday the 13th.
十三号星期五
The Pope sent troops to claim the Priory's treasure...
教宗派军队夺取锡安会的宝物
but they found nothing.
但是却什么也没找到
The few surviving Knights of the Priory had vanished...
幸免于难的圣殿骑士从此消失
and the search for their sacred artifact began again.
圣物的搜寻行动就此展开
What artifact? I've never heard about any of this.
什么圣物? 我从来没有听过
Yes, you have.
你当然有听过
Almost everyone on earth has.
世上每个人都有听过
You just know it as the Holy Grail.
这件圣物就是传说中的圣杯
Please, Sauniere thought he knew the location of the Holy Grail?
索尼耶赫认为他知道圣杯的下落
Maybe more than that.
也许不只如此
This cross and the flower, this could be very old. But look.
这个十字架也许非常古老
This metal here underneath is much newer, and there's a modern ID stamp.
不过底下金属的部份比较新 而且有现代化的身份识别记号
"Haxo 24."
阿克索24
And these dots. These dots are read by a laser.
这些小洞是用来让雷射读取的
This is more than a pendant. This is a key your grandfather left you.
这不只是一个坠饰 而是你祖父留给你的钥匙
He left us, professor.
他留给我们两个人的
And vingt-quatre Haxo, it's not an ID stamp.
阿克索24不是身份识别记号
It's a street address.
而是一个地址
This is Jacques Sauniere.
这是贾克索尼耶赫
Please leave a message after the tone.
请在哔声后留言
Please, Monsieur Sauniere, pick up the phone.
索尼耶赫先生 请接电话
This is Sandrine Bieil.
我是桑德琳碧耶
I have called the list.
我打给名单上的每个人
I fear the other guardians are dead.
其他的大长老都死了
The lie has been told.
他们向杀人凶手说谎
The floor panel has been broken.
那块地板也被敲碎
Please, monsieur, pick up the phone. I beg you.
求求你 快接电话
Job 38, verse 11.
《约伯记》三十八章十一节
Do you know it, Sister?
你会背吗?
Job 38:11.
《约伯记》三十八章十一节
Hitherto shalt thou come...
你只可到这里
but no further.
不可越过
"But no further."
"不可越过"
Do you mock me?
你在耍我吗?
Where is the keystone?
拱心石在哪里?
I do not know.
我不知道
No.
不
You are a sister of the Church...
你是教会的修女
and yet you serve them: The Priory.
但是却对锡安会效忠?
Jesus had but one true message. That...
耶稣只有一个真正的讯息...
Come, you saints of God.
上帝的圣徒
Hasten, angels of the Lord.
天主派来的天使
To receive her soul.
请接收她的灵魂
And bring her to the sight of the Almighty.
将她带到全能上帝的怀抱
In the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
以圣父 圣子 圣灵之名 阿们
Welcome, bishop.
欢迎 主教
May Christ be with you.
愿主与你同在
And also with you.
也与你同在
It's been too long, Manuel.
曼纽 好久不见了
I saw your press conference.
我看到你的记者会
Very priestly.
很有神父的样子
Vultures.
一群秃鹰
But you need a good cover to fly into Italy these days.
但这些时日 去意大利 得要有好的形象
So how are things in Rome?
罗马状况如何?
We serve at his pleasure.
我们服侍他
Today is today.
今天只是今天
But there are many tomorrows.
但还有许许多多的明天
Vatican cellars.
梵蒂冈酒窖
1976.
1976年
Seventy-six, a year of independence. How fitting.
1976 独立的一年 真是恰当
I thought you'd like it.
我就知道你会喜欢
I'll fetch the others.
我叫其他人过来
Welcome, bishop.
欢迎 主教
This council is convened.
会议开始
Our words shall never pass these walls.
今天讨论的事必须守口如瓶
What business, say you?
你要说什么事?
As you know, my request for funds...
我要求的款项...
Yes, 20 million euro in untraceable bearer bonds.
面额两千万欧元的不记名债券
A tad more than petty cash. Wouldn't you say, bishop?
这不算是一笔小钱 不是吗?
The endeavor is complex. Freedom has a high cost.
这任务很复杂 自由的代价很高
And, of course, you will deliver us.
当然 你会拯救我们
How fortunate we are.
我们真是幸运
I only offer a route to the renewal of faith for all men.
我只是帮助全人类重拾信仰
How humble.
你还真谦虚
Our savior, Bishop Aringarosa.
救世主艾林葛若萨主教
Were we to grant your request...
若我们同意你的要求...
when would this mission commence?
任务会在何时开始行动?
- Actually, tonight. - What?
- 今晚就会开始 - 什么?
- It has begun. - We have not agreed.
- 它已经开始了 - 我们还没同意
How dare you presume to...
你竟敢妄想...
I do not presume, I act!
我不会妄想 只会行动
The Vatican's unwillingness to support us...
梵蒂冈不愿意支持我们
is both impious and cowardly.
非但不虔诚而且懦弱
Blood is being spilled because true Christian values lie in ruins. No more!
基督教价值观瓦解才会流血 我不能忍受下去
This council has forgotten its very purpose.
你们都忘记我们的任务
Tonight...
今晚
the Grail will be destroyed.
圣杯将被摧毁
The Priory's few remaining members will be silenced.
锡安会的会员将被消灭
I was contacted by a man who calls himself only "the Teacher."
一位自称为老师的人和我联络
He knows a great deal about this council.
他对这个议会了解甚多
And about the Priory.
还有锡安会
Two prostitutes identified Langdon and Neveu...
两个妓女看到兰登和纳佛
getting into a taxi in the Bois de Boulogne.
在布洛涅森林搭计程车
Because of your expertise?
是因为你的专业知识吗?
- I'm sorry? - About the Priory.
- 你说什么? - 你知道锡安会的来历
Do you think that's why Sauniere sought you out?
所以索尼耶赫才会找你?
I can think of dozens of scholars who know a lot more about it.
有好几十名学者懂的比我更多
Actually, I didn't think he liked me very much.
而且我觉得他也不太喜欢我
Once made a joke at my expense. Got a big laugh out of it.
他甚至拿我说过一个笑话
What was it?
什么笑话?
How may I help you?
我能效劳吗?
The door to the right, please.
请用右手边的门
(头号通缉犯)
That was quite a performance.
真是场精采的表演
The little shit should know better than to play politics with me.
那些垃圾该知道别跟我耍手段
I know I got in front of you, old friend.
我知道我挡到你的路 老友
I did what I thought was best.
我做了我认为是最好的决定
So...
那么...
now what?
现在怎么办?
Now we wait for the Teacher's call.
现在我们就等老师电话
Good evening. I am Andre Vernet, the night manager.
晚安 我是夜间经理安德烈维贺内
I take it this is your first visit to our establishment?
我猜这是你们第一次光临本银行
Yes.
没错
Understood.
了解
Keys are often passed on and first-time users...
钥匙通常会传给下一代
are sometimes uncertain of protocol.
第一次使用的客人不清楚程序
Keys are essentially numbered Swiss accounts.
钥匙就像瑞士银行帐户
Often willed through generations.
通常会传承好几代
Is it yours, mademoiselle?
这是你的帐户吗?
The shortest safety-deposit-box lease is 50 years.
保险箱租期至少是五十年
And what's your longest account?
最长的租期是多久?
Quite a bit longer.
非常非常久
Technologies change, keys are updated.
随着科技进步 钥匙也有修改
But our accounts date back to the beginning of banking itself.
但是我们的帐户 可追溯到银行业发源时
Once the computer confirms your key...
电脑确认钥匙上的标记后
enter your account number and your box is retrieved.
输入帐号就可以取出保险箱
The room is yours, as long as you like.
这间房间要用久多行
What if I lost track of my account number?
如果我忘了帐号怎么办?
How might I recover it?
我该怎么重新询问?
I'm afraid each key is paired with a 10-digit number...
每把钥匙都搭配十位数的帐号
known only to the account bearer.
只有帐户主人才知道
I hope you manage to remember it.
我希望你记得起来
A single wrong entry disables the system.
输入错误帐号 系统就会关闭
- Ten. - Ten.
- 十个数字 - 十个数字
Your grandfather's Fibonacci sequence.
你祖父的斐波那契数列
Scrambled, unscrambled?
是没弄乱的还是弄乱的数列?
Unscrambled.
没弄乱的数列
It's your key.
这是你的钥匙
Funny, I don't even like history.
真讽刺 我根本就不喜欢历史
I've never seen much good come from looking to the past.
我认为回顾过去没什么好处
Moment of truth.
决定成败的一刻
(正确)
My God. I don't believe this.
天啊 我不敢相信
A rose.
玫瑰
The rose was a symbol for the Holy Grail.
玫瑰是圣杯的象征
Forgive the intrusion.
抱歉打扰了
I'm afraid the police arrived more quickly than I anticipated.
警方来得比我想像的快
You must follow me, please.
请你们跟我来
For your own safety.
这是为了你们的安全
You knew they were coming?
你知道他们会来?
My guard alerted me to your status when you arrived.
你们一到就被警卫认出来
Yours is one of our oldest and highest-level accounts.
这是最古老 层级最高的帐户
It includes a safe-passage clause.
包含了安全逃亡的条款
Safe passage?
安全逃亡?
If you would step inside, please. Time is of the essence.
请进来 时间紧迫
In there?
进去那里?
Hey, is there a problem?
有问题吗?
Good evening, sir. Police.
晚安 我是警察
I just drive from here to Zurich. Not French, English?
我才刚开车来苏黎世 法文不太行 你说英文吗?
- English? - Yes.
- 英文? - 是的
We are looking for two criminals.
我们在找两名罪犯
You came to the right place. They're all criminals here.
你来对地方了 到处都是罪犯
Would you mind opening the hold?
请你打开后车厢
Please. You think they trust us, the wages I get paid?
他们怎么会信任我这个小司机?
You don't have keys to your own truck?
你没有后车厢的钥匙?
It's armored. Keys get sent to the destination.
这是运钞车 钥匙都送到目的地
You mind? I'm on a schedule here.
拜托你 我得赶时间
And do all the drivers wear a Rolex?
司机怎么会戴劳力士表?
What?
什么?
This piece of shit.
这是仿冒品啦
Forty euros in Barbes.
花四十欧元在地摊买的
Yours for 35.
我卖你三十五欧元
No, no, no.
不...
- Thirty. - No. It's okay, it's okay.
- 三十欧元 - 不要 没关系
Come on, 30, eh?
三十欧元要不要?
I said, no!
我说过 不要!
Move along!
给我走吧
Now we wait.
我们要耐心等待 老师会告诉我
The Teacher will call and tell me where to deliver the money.
把钱送到哪里
You have put tremendous faith in this Teacher of yours.
你对这位老师很有信心嘛
Yes, I have. And I have given him an angel to do his will.
是的 我也给他一名天使替他做事
For surely there is no better soldier for God than my Silas.
没有比西拉更好的士兵了
I firmly resolve, with the help of thy grace, to confess my sins...
我仰赖天父的帮助 坚决认罪并接受惩罚
to do penance and to amend my life.
替自己赎罪
Amen.
阿门
I chastise my body.
我严格的对付自己的身体
The Holy Grail.
圣杯
A magic cup. The source of God's power on earth.
神奇的酒杯 上帝在世上的权力来源
It's nonsense.
全是胡扯淡
You don't believe in God.
你不相信上帝
No.
没错
I don't believe in some magic from the sky.
我不相信天上掉下来的魔术
Just people.
我只相信人
Sometimes that they can be kind.
有时候人是善良的
And that's enough?
这样就够了吗?
Well, I think it has to be. I think it's all we have.
非够不可 我们只拥有这些
Are you a God-fearing man, professor?
你敬畏上帝吗?
I was raised a Catholic.
我出身在天主教家庭
Well, that's not really an answer.
那不算是回答
Professor, are you okay?
教授 你没事吧?
Go ahead, open it.
打开来吧
Go on.
快呀
A cryptex.
藏密筒
They are used to keep secrets.
用来储藏秘密文件
It's da Vinci's design.
这是达芬奇的设计
You write the information on a papyrus scroll...
把秘密资料写在莎草纸上面
which is then rolled around a thin glass vial of vinegar.
然后卷住装满醋的小玻璃管
If you force it open, the vial breaks...
硬要打开就会打碎玻璃管
vinegar dissolves papyrus...
纸草卷也会被醋溶解
and your secret is lost forever.
你的秘密就会永远消失
The only way to access the information...
安全取得秘密唯一的方法
is to spell out the password...
就是用这五个转盘拼出密码
with these five dials, each with 26 letters.
每个转盘有二十六个字母
That's 12 million possibilities.
一共有一千两百万个可能
I've never met a girl who knew that much about a cryptex.
我没见过这么了解藏密筒的女生
Sauniere made one for me once.
索尼耶赫替我做过一个
My grandfather gave me a wagon.
我祖父只替我做过玩具马车
This clearly is not the Holy Grail.
这很显然不是圣杯
Come on.
我受够了
Please, you're not all right.
你整个人都很不对劲
May I try something?
让我试个方法帮帮你
I don't know why it works.
我不知道为什么会有效
My mother used to do it when I was scared, I think.
不过我害怕时我妈都会这么做
You think?
真的吗?
Yes.
没错
Feeling better, Sophie?
苏菲 好多了吗?
My parents died in a car crash with my brother.
我父母和我哥哥死于车祸
I was 4.
当时我才四岁
I'm sorry.
很遗憾
It was many years ago.
那是好多年前的事
Better?
好多了吗?
Yeah.
好多了
Okay.
好吧
Twenty years waiting for someone to come for that box...
这二十年来我一直在等人 来拿这个玩意儿
and now it's you two murderers. Bring it to me.
结果是你们这两个杀人犯 交给我
I don't know what you're talking about.
我不知道你在说什么
All right! Okay!
好啦 好啦
Right now!
快点
Step back!
退回去
No one will lose sleep over a couple on a killing spree.
没人会可怜两个杀人凶手
Turn around.
转过去
Turn around!
快转过去
You too, mademoiselle.
你也一样
Sophie!
苏菲
Get in the truck!
上车
I'll drive! Hurry!
我来开车 快点
- Better? - Always, if I got too nervous...
- 好点了吗? - 当我太紧张时 我总得...
I had to put my head out of the window not to be sick.
把头伸出窗外 才不会想吐
Sauniere used to say I was like a dog.
索尼耶赫总说我像只狗一样
A cute dog. You know, a little dog.
是可爱的狗 你知道 是小狗
What happened between you and your grandfather, Sophie?
你和你祖父到底发生什么事?
I've jammed my shoulder, I've been shot at, I'm bleeding.
我的肩膀受伤 被人开枪 现在还在流血
I need to know.
我有权知道真相
You say he raised you, but you two don't talk anymore.
他把你养大 你们却不再联络
You call him by his last name.
而且你直接叫他的姓氏
You say you hate history.
你还说你不喜欢历史
Nobody hates history. They hate their own histories.
没有人讨厌历史 他们只会痛恨自己的过去
So now you're a psychologist too?
你又变成心理医生了吗?
What if Sauniere had started to groom you for the Priory?
也许他想把你训练成锡安会员
What do you mean, groom me?
你这是什么意思?
Your grandfather gave you puzzles and cryptex as a child.
你从小他就送你藏密筒和字谜
Say Sauniere was hoping one day you would join him in the Priory.
看来索尼耶赫希望你有一天 能到锡安会加入他
Still, years later, when he imagines...
但多年后 当他认为...
the Grail is in danger, he reaches out to you.
圣杯有危险 还是来找你
So you are saying all this is real? The Priory, the Holy Grail?
你认为这一切都是真的? 锡安会和圣杯?
We've been dragged into a world of people who think this stuff is real.
至少这些人都认为是真的
- Real enough to kill for. - Who?
- 而且愿意杀人灭口 - 到底是谁?
I'm out of my field here.
这我就不知道了
I do know a Grail historian, absolutely obsessed with Priory myth.
我只认识一个圣杯历史学家 他对锡安会传说非常着迷
An Englishman, lives here in France.
他是住在法国的英国佬
Do you trust this man?
你信任这个人吗?
I hope you can.
我希望你能信任他
Vernet, Andre.
安德烈维贺内
It seems you're not a driver at all.
你不只是一个司机嘛
Apparently, you lost your tongue along with your truck.
货车不见了 你连话都不能说了
Aiding and abetting two murder suspects.
你协助两名逃犯 是共犯 我能把你关起来
That carries jail time.
去跟我的律师说吧
Speak to my lawyer.
我可以 但这样的混乱与暴力 还有货车被偷
All this confusion, violence, vanishing property...
贵银行的某些顾客 可能会觉得服务...
It might get around that your bank is less than ideal, don't you think?
远不及你们的美名
You think you're in pain now, Andre Vernet?
这种痛苦还只是小意思
My cause is worth your life. Understand?
我随时都可以杀了你 明白吗?
What do you want?
你想干嘛?
Your truck carries a homing device. Activate it.
你的货车装了追踪器 把它开启
Please wait. I'll see if he's available.
请稍候 我去看他有没有空
It's on the wrong side.
对讲机放错边了
Leigh likes all things to be English, including his cars.
李伊喜欢英国制度 包括开车
Robert! Do I owe you money?
罗柏 我欠你钱吗?
Leigh, my friend...
李伊 老友
care to open up for an old colleague?
帮你的老同事开门 好吗?
- Of course. - Thank you.
- 没问题 - 谢谢
But first, a test of honor.
不过我要先考你一下
Three questions.
三个问题
Fire away.
问吧
Your first:
第一个问题
Shall I serve coffee or tea?
我要招待咖啡或茶?
Tea, of course.
当然是茶?
Excellent.
非常好
Second: Milk or lemon?
第二题 要加牛奶或柠檬片?
Milk?
牛奶吗?
That would depend on the tea.
这要看我们喝哪一种茶
Correct.
答对了
And now the third and most grave of inquiries:
第三个也是最重要的问题
In which year did a Harvard sculler outrow an Oxford man at Henley?
哈佛大学划船队在哪一年 击败牛津大学队?
Surely such a travesty has never occurred.
这么扯的事不可能会发生
Your heart is true.
你果然是好朋友
You may pass.
请进吧
Welcome to Chateau Villette.
欢迎光临威雷特堡
Leigh Teabing has spent his entire life...
李伊提宝用他的一辈子...
studying the Grail. That thing is one hot tamale.
研究圣杯 它真是炙手可热
Sorry?
你说什么?
The cryptex, it's a hot coal.
藏密筒 它炙手可热
A hot potato?
是烫手山芋?
So you want to keep our chest close to our cards, yes?
所以你才要把底牌盖起来 是吗?
Very close.
差不多是这样
The truck's signal is coming online.
接收到货车的追踪讯号了
It's about time.
这才像话嘛
Locked on and tracking, sir.
正在进行追踪
(威雷特)
Very good. Tell Collet not to move in until I get there.
太好了 通知科列等我到了才能行动
Attention! All of Collet's units to Chateau Villette.
注意 立刻前往威雷特堡
The suspects Neveu and Langdon are likely at that location.
两名嫌犯很可能在那里
Aringarosa.
我是艾林葛若萨
I still don't know why he put you into this...
我不知道他为什么把你扯进来
and I'm sorry.
真的很抱歉
But...
不过...
l'm also very glad.
我也很高兴
You are requested to make yourself at home.
请两位把这里当自己的家
Robert!
罗柏!
And you travel with a maiden, it seems.
你带了一个美眉来
Sir Leigh Teabing, may I present Miss Sophie Neveu.
李伊 这是苏菲纳佛小姐
Sophie, Sir Leigh Teabing.
苏菲 这位是李伊提宝爵士
It's an honor to welcome you...
我很荣幸欢迎你
even though it's late.
虽然时候已经不早了
Thank you for having us. I realize it's quite late.
谢谢你的招待 现在来打扰你真的太晚了
So late, mademoiselle, it's almost early.
晚到几乎都快要天亮了
What a lovely smile you have.
你的笑容真美
Earl Grey?
伯爵茶?
Lemon.
加柠檬片
Correct.
答对了
Chateau Villette. Yes.
威雷特堡 对
- No. - Oh, you must.
- 不 - 你一定要
Remy is from Lyons, but nevertheless...
黑密从里昂来 话虽如此
he is fantastic with sauces.
他很会做酱汁
- Thank you. - No, I can't.
- 谢谢 - 不 我不行了
A dramatic late-night arrival.
两位星夜来访
Mention of life and death.
讲到生与死
What can an old cripple do for you, Robert?
我这老瘸子能帮什么忙?
We wanna talk about the Priory of Sion.
我们想谈谈锡安会
The keepers?
守护者?
The secret war?
秘密的战争?
Sorry for all the mystery.
很抱歉搞得这么神秘
Leigh, I'm into something here that I cannot understand.
不过我被卷入一桩我不懂的事情
You?
你?
- Really? - Not without your help.
- 有你不懂的事情? - 这件事只有你最懂
Playing to my vanity, Robert. You should be ashamed.
你用捧我这一招真不要脸
Not if it works.
只要有用就行
There are always four:
一向都有四名守护者
The Grand Master and the three Senechaux...
盟主和三名大长老
make up the primary guardians of the Grail.
他们是圣杯的守护者
Thank you, Remy. That'll be all for now.
谢谢你 黑密 你去休息吧
The Priory's members span our very globe itself.
锡安会会员遍布世界各地
Philippe de Cherisey exposed that as a hoax in 1967.
斐里伯迪切若西在一九六七年 证明锡安会是假的
And that is what they want you to believe.
他们就是要世人这么想
The Priory is charged with a single task:
锡安会只有一个任务
To protect the greatest secret in modern history.
保护近代史最大的秘密
The source of God's power on earth.
上帝在这世上的权力来源
No, that's a common misunderstanding.
不 这是一般人的误解
The Priory protects the source of the Church's power on earth:
锡安会负责保护的是... 罗马教廷在世上的权力来源
The Holy Grail.
圣杯
I don't understand.
我不懂
What power? Some magic dishes?
什么权力来源? 圣杯有魔法力量吗?
Robert. Has he been telling you that the Holy Grail is a cup?
罗柏 他告诉你说圣杯是杯子吗?
To understand the Holy Grail, my dear...
亲爱的 要了解圣杯
you must first understand the Holy Bible.
你一定得先了解圣经
The Good Book did not arrive by facsimile from heaven.
《圣经》不是从天堂传真下来的
The Bible as we know it was finally presided over by one man:
我们所知的《圣经》是 由一个人编纂而成
The pagan emperor Constantine.
异教徒皇帝君士坦丁大帝
I thought Constantine was a Christian.
我以为君士坦丁大帝是基督徒
Oh, hardly, no. He was a lifelong pagan...
并不是 他一辈子都是异教徒
who was baptized on his deathbed.
临终前才受洗
Constantine was Rome's supreme holy man.
他是罗马地位最崇高的大祭司
From time immemorial...
从远古以来
his people had worshiped a balance between nature's male deities...
罗马人就崇拜自然界的男神
and the goddess, or sacred feminine.
以及女神或是女圣者
But a growing religious turmoil was gripping Rome.
但是后来罗马帝国发生宗教纷争
Three centuries earlier...
君士坦丁统治的三百年前
a young Jew named Jesus had come along...
一个叫耶稣的犹太青年出现
preaching love and a single God.
传递大爱与一神论的道理
Centuries after his crucifixion...
他被钉上十字架的三百多年后
Christ's followers had grown exponentially...
基督的信徒日益增多
and had started a religious war against the pagans.
和异教徒展开一场宗教大战
Or did the pagans commence war against the Christians?
或者是异教徒向基督教徒宣战?
Leigh, we can't be sure who began the atrocities in that period.
我们不能确定到底是谁先开战
We can at least agree that the conflict grew to such proportions...
不过至少能确定冲突愈来愈严重
that it threatened to tear Rome in two.
足以将罗马帝国分裂成两半
So Constantine may have been a lifelong pagan...
君士坦丁也许一辈子是异教徒
but he was also a pragmatist.
不过他也是务实主义者
And in 325 anno Domini...
他在西元三百二十五年决定
he decided to unify Rome under a single religion, Christianity.
将罗马帝国统合在单一宗教之下 也就是基督教
Christianity was on the rise. He didn't want his empire torn apart.
基督教的势力日益强大 他不想让罗马帝国四分五裂
And to strengthen this new Christian tradition...
他为了强化全新的基督教传统
Constantine held a famous ecumenical gathering...
举办了一次著名的基督教界会议
known as the Council of Nicaea.
世人所知的尼西亚大公会议
And at this council...
在这次会议中
the many sects of Christianity debated and voted on, well...
基督教的不同教派进行辩论及投票
everything, from the acceptance and rejection of specific gospels...
表决的事项包括采纳哪些福音
to the date for Easter...
以及复活节的日期
to the administering of the sacraments, and of course...
乃至于圣礼内容 当然还有...
the immortality of Jesus.
耶稣的神性
I don't follow.
我不懂
Well, ma chere, until that moment in history...
亲爱的 一直到那个时候
Jesus was viewed by many of his followers as a mighty prophet...
耶稣被许多信徒视为伟大的先知
as a great and powerful man, but a man nevertheless.
以及影响力深远的伟人 不过只是一个凡人
A mortal man.
一个会死亡的凡人
Some Christians held that Jesus was mortal.
有些基督徒认为耶稣是凡人
Some Christians believed he was divine.
有些基督徒相信祂是神
Not the Son of God?
不是神的儿子?
Not even his nephew twice removed.
连祂的表外甥都算不上
Hold on, you're saying Jesus' divinity came from a vote.
等等 你是说耶稣的神性 是投票选出来的
Well, remember, in those days, gods were everywhere.
你得记得 在那时代 无处不是神只
By infusing Jesus the man with the divine magic...
在耶稣身上注入神性
by making him capable of earthly miracles...
让祂能在人间显神迹
as well as his own resurrection, Constantine turned him into a god...
并得以重生 君士坦丁把祂变成了神
but within the human world.
在人间的神
And he basically knocked the more distant gods out of the game.
基本上祂击败了所有 远在天边的神只
Constantine did not create Jesus' divinity.
君士坦丁没有创造耶稣的神性
He simply sanctioned an already widely held idea.
只是认可已经广为流传的信仰
- Semantics. - No, it's not semantics.
- 只是说法不同而已 - 不只是说法不同
You're interpreting facts to support your own conclusions.
你扭曲事实来支持你的结论
Fact: For many Christians, Jesus was mortal one day and divine the next.
事实是对许多基督徒而言 耶稣有时候是神 有时候是人
For some Christians, his divinity was enhanced.
许多信徒坚信他的神性无庸置疑
Absurd. There was a formal announcement of his promotion.
胡说八道 他们甚至发布 正式敕令建立他的神性
They couldn't even agree on the Nicene Creed!
他们连对尼西亚信经都有歧见
Excuse me. "Who is God, who is man?"
等一下 谁是神? 谁是人?
How many have been murdered over this question?
有多少人因为这问题被杀害?
As long as there has been a one true God...
当至高无上的神一出现
there has been killing in his name.
就有人以祂之名进行杀戮
Now let me show you the Grail.
让我给你看圣杯
This used to be the ballroom.
这里原本是舞厅
I have little occasion to dance these days.
这些年我很少有机会跳舞
I trust you recognize The Last Supper...
你一定看过 最后的晚餐
the great fresco by Leonardo da Vinci.
达芬奇伟大的湿壁画
Now, my dear, if you would close your eyes.
亲爱的 请你闭上眼睛
Oh, Leigh, save us the parlor tricks.
李伊 别耍这种花招
You asked for my help, I recall.
我记得是你来找我帮忙的
Allow an old man his indulgences.
你就让一个老头子玩一玩吧
Now, mademoiselle, where is Jesus sitting?
小姐 耶稣坐在哪里?
- In the middle. - Good.
- 在中央 - 很好
He and his disciples are breaking bread.
他和门徒在分食面包
And what drink?
他们喝什么?
Wine. They drank wine.
他们喝的是葡萄酒
Splendid. And one final question:
非常好 最后一个问题
How many wineglasses are there on the table?
桌上有几个酒杯?
One? The Holy Grail?
一个? 圣杯?
Open your eyes.
张开眼睛
No single cup.
桌上不是只有一个酒杯
No chalice.
是根本没有
Well, that's a bit strange, isn't it?
这有点奇怪 对吧?
Considering both the Bible and standard Grail legend...
因为根据《圣经》和圣杯传说
celebrate this moment as the definitive arrival of the Holy Grail.
这都是圣杯出现的关键时刻
Now, Robert, you could be of help to us.
罗柏 轮到你上场了
If you'd be so kind as to show us the symbols for man and woman, please.
请你比出代表男女的符号
No balloon animals. I can make a great duck.
我不会比手影 只会比手划脚
This is the original icon for male. It's a rudimentary phallus.
这是代表男性的原始符号 其实是阳具的象征
- Quite to the point. - Yes, indeed.
- 非常具体 - 一点也没错
This is known as the blade.
这个符号被称为刀刃
It represents aggression and manhood.
代表侵略性和男子气概
It's a symbol still used today in modern military uniforms.
至今仍用在现代军服上面
Yes, the more penises you have, the higher your rank. Boys will be boys.
你的老二愈多 军阶就愈高 男人就是这么幼稚
Now, as you would imagine, the female symbol is its exact opposite.
你可以想像 女性符号正好相反
This is called the chalice.
这被称为圣爵
And the chalice resembles a cup or vessel or, more importantly...
圣爵的形状像杯子或容器 更重要的是
the shape of a woman's womb.
它像女人的子宫
No, the Grail has never been a cup.
圣杯从来就不是一个杯子
It is quite literally this ancient symbol of womanhood.
而是这个古代的女性象征符号
And in this case, a woman who carried a secret so powerful...
在这里指的是一个女人 她怀有重大的秘密
that if revealed, it would devastate the very foundations of Christianity.
秘密一旦揭露 就会摧毁基督教的根基
Wait, please.
等一下
You're saying the Holy Grail is a person? A woman?
你是说圣杯是一个人? 一个女人?
And it turns out, she makes an appearance right there.
其实她早就出现在画作上面
But they are all men.
他们都是男人呀
Are they?
是吗?
What about that figure on the right hand of our Lord...
坐在主耶稣右手边
seated in the place of honor?
也就是最上座的那个人呢?
Flowing red hair.
柔顺的红色长发
Folded feminine hands.
女性化的双手交叠
Hint of a bosom. No?
加上看起来像女人的胸部
It's called scotoma. The mind sees what it chooses to see.
这就是所谓的盲点 大脑只看到它选择看的东西
Who is she?
她是谁?
My dear, that's Mary Magdalene.
她就是抹大拉的马利亚
The prostitute?
那个妓女?
She was no such thing.
她并不是妓女
Smeared by the Church in 591 anno Domini, poor dear.
教会在西元五百九十一年抹黑她 真可怜
Mary Magdalene was Jesus' wife.
抹大拉的马利亚是耶稣的妻子
This is an old wives' tale.
这是一个古老的谣传
The original one, in fact.
也是最初的传言
There's virtually no empirical proof.
这谣传完全没有证据
He knows as well as I do there's much evidence to support it.
他明明知道有很多证据
Theories. There are theories.
纯粹是推论
Notice how Jesus and Mary are clothed.
仔细看耶稣和马利亚的衣服
Mirror images of each other.
就像是对方的镜像
The mind sees what it chooses to see.
大脑只看到它选择看的东西
And venturing into the even more bizarre, notice how Jesus and Mary...
更诡异的是 你再看耶稣和马利亚
appear to be joined at the hip and are leaning away from each other...
臀部连在一起 身体却往反方向倾斜
as if to create a shape in the negative space between them.
他们这种姿势形成一个形状
Leonardo gives us the chalice.
达芬奇画出圣爵的符号
Yes. Oh, and Robert, notice what happens...
罗柏 请注意看
when these two figures change position.
他们交换位置会是什么样子
Just because da Vinci painted it doesn't make it true.
达芬奇这么画不代表这是事实
No. But history...
没错 但是历史...
she does make it true.
有证据
Now, listen to this. It's from the Gospel according to Philip.
听好了 这出自《腓力福音》
Philip?
《腓力福音》?
Yes, it was rejected at the Council of Nicaea...
它和其它的福音
along with any other gospels that made...
在尼西亚大公会议上被删去
Jesus appear human and not divine.
因为它们把耶稣形容为凡人
"And the companion of the Savior is Mary Magdalene.
救世主的同伴是抹大拉的马利亚
Christ loved her more than all the disciples...
基督爱她胜过所有门徒
and used to kiss her on the..."
习于不时亲她的...
But this says nothing of marriage.
但这段话没说他们结婚
Well, actually...
其实呢...
Robert.
罗柏
Actually, in those days, the word "companion" literally meant "spouse."
当时同伴这个字的意思就是配偶
And this is from the Gospel of Mary Magdalene herself.
这出自 《抹大拉的马利亚福音》
- She wrote a gospel? - She may have.
- 她写了一部福音书? - 也许有吧
- Robert, will you fight fair? - She may have.
- 请你说话公平一点 - 她也许有写过
"And Peter said, 'Did he prefer her to us? '
彼得说"他喜欢她胜过我们吗? "
And Levi answered:
利未回答
'Peter, I see you contending against a woman like an adversary.
你把一个女人当成竞争敌手
If the Savior made her worthy, who are you, indeed, to reject her?"'
如果救世主这么重视她 你凭什么厌弃她?
Yes. And then, my dear, Jesus goes on to tell Mary Magdalene...
没错 然后耶稣告诉抹大拉的马利亚
that it's up to her to continue his Church.
她要在他死后带领他的教会
Mary Magdalene, not Peter.
是抹大拉的马利亚 不是彼得
The Church was supposed to be carried on by a woman.
基督教教会本来是要由女人带领
Few realize that Mary was descended from kings, just as her husband was.
很少人知道马利亚是王室后裔 就跟耶稣一样
Now, my dear, the word in French for Holy Grail.
亲爱的 圣杯的法文怎么说?
From the Middle English "Sangreal"...
字源是中古世纪英语
of the original Arthurian legend.
出自于亚瑟王传说
Now, as two words. Can you translate for our friend?
请你把这两个字翻译给他听
Sang real, it means "royal blood."
这两个字的意思是王室之血
When the legend speaks of the chalice that held the blood of Christ...
传说中装过基督之血的圣杯
it speaks in fact of the female womb that carried Jesus' royal bloodline.
其实指的是 怀着耶稣王室血脉的女性子宫
But how could Christ have a bloodline, unless...?
基督怎么会有血脉 除非...
Mary was pregnant at the time of the Crucifixion.
马利亚在耶稣死前就怀了孕
For her own safety and for that of Christ's unborn child...
为了保护她自己 和基督未出世的孩子
she fled the Holy Land and came to France.
她从圣地逃到法国
And here, it is said, she gave birth to a daughter, Sarah.
据说她在这里 生下一个女儿 名叫莎拉
They know the child's name.
他们知道那孩子的名字
- A little girl. - Yes.
- 一个小女孩 - 没错
If that were true, it's adding insult to injury.
如果是真的 教会的羞辱就更大
Why?
为什么?
The pagans found transcendence through the joining of male to female.
异教徒透过男女结合体验到神圣
People found God through sex?
透过性交寻找上帝?
In paganism, women were worshiped as a route to heaven...
他们相信能透过女人通往天国
but the modern Church has a monopoly on that...
现代教会却垄断这权力
in salvation through Jesus Christ.
宣称只能透过耶稣基督获得救赎
And he who keeps the keys to heaven rules the world.
握有通往天国之钥者统治世界
Women, then, are a huge threat to the Church.
女人在当时对教会造成威胁
The Catholic Inquisition soon publishes...
天主教宗教法庭出版...
what may be the most blood-soaked book in human history.
人类史上害死最多人的著作
The Malleus Maleficarum.
锄恶利器
The Witches' Hammer.
也就是《女巫之捶》
It instructed the clergy on how to locate, torture and kill...
教人如何找出 拷问并杀害...
all freethinking women.
拥有独立思想的女性
In three centuries of witch hunts...
长达三世纪的猎女巫行动
50,000 women are captured, burned alive at the stake.
共有五万名女子被活活烧死
Oh, at least that. Some say millions.
那是保守估计 有人说数百万
Imagine, then, Robert...
你想像一下 罗柏
that Christ's throne might live on in a female child.
基督的王位由他的女儿继承
You asked what would be worth killing for.
你问我是什么让人们大开杀戒
Witness the greatest cover-up in human history.
就是历史上最大的掩饰行动
This is the secret that the Priory of Sion...
这也是锡安会两千年来
has defended for over 20 centuries.
竭力保守的秘密
They are the guardians of the royal bloodline.
他们是王室后裔的守护者
The keepers of the proof of our true past.
扞卫事实真相的证据
They are the protectors of the living descendants of Jesus Christ...
他们负责保护耶稣基督...
and Mary Magdalene.
和抹大拉的马利亚的后代
Sir Leigh?
李伊爵士?
Sometimes I wonder who is serving whom.
有时候我真不知道谁才是主人
His sauces are not that fantastic.
他烧的菜其实没那么好吃
Yes, can I help you?
什么事?
Yes. They're on the news now.
他们上了电视新闻
Living descendants? Is it possible?
耶稣的后代? 有可能吗?
It's not impossible.
并不是不可能
You have not been honest with me. Your pictures are on the television.
你们没有对我坦白 电视上有你们的通缉照片
You are wanted for four murders!
你们涉嫌杀死四个人
That's why Vernet said "killing spree."
怪不得维贺内说我们大开杀戒
You come into my home, playing on my passions for the Grail.
你们利用我对圣杯的热衷兴趣
- That's why he needed you. - You will leave my house!
- 所以他才需要你 苏菲 - 立刻离开我家
- Leigh, listen! - No, I'm calling the police.
- 李伊 听我说 - 不 我要报警
Jacques Sauniere was her grandfather.
贾克索尼耶赫是她的祖父
You're the obsessive Priory scholar.
你是专门研究锡安会的学者
You still keep lists of who might be in the Priory?
一定知道谁有可能是成员
I'll bet Jacques Sauniere was on one of those lists.
我打赌索尼耶赫在你的名单上
He was on your list of who could be Grand Master, wasn't he?
你认为他可能是锡安会盟主
- What? - I'll bet he was right at the top.
- 什么? - 他是你的头号人选
Consider: Four men murdered? The same number as the guardians.
有四个人被谋杀 和守护者的人数一样
What if the Priory was compromised, the other Senechaux dead?
也许锡安会的身份曝光 其他的大长老也遇害了
What if you yourself were dying, a Grand Master?
假设你是临死前的盟主
You'd have to pass the secret on to someone you could trust.
一定会把秘密传给你能信任的人
Someone outside the society.
不属于锡安会的人
Maybe someone whose training you had begun but never finished.
也许你已经开始训练这个人 却一直没有完成
Robert, your ruse is pathetic.
罗柏 你编的谎话太扯了
Not really.
不尽然
No, that's impossible.
不 不可能
Can that really...?
这真的是...
Is it the keystone?
这是拱心石吗?
I'll even show it to you, Leigh.
我可以给你看
Will you just tell us what the hell it's for?
拜托你告诉我它是用来做什么的
Fache says to wait, so I wait.
法舍叫我等我就等
What's Fache thinking? The truck is here. They're inside.
法舍在想什么? 货车在这里 他们在里面
Yes.
没错
As the legend foretold:
就跟传说预言的一样
"It hides beneath the Rose."
它藏在玫瑰的标志之下
Oh, my.
天啊
Leigh.
李伊
Leigh?
Please.
求求你
I'm sorry. Yes, of course.
抱歉 没问题
Inside the keystone...
拱心石里面...
there'll be a map.
有一张地图
A map that will lead us to the Holy Grail.
可以带我们找到圣杯
To be trained by the Grand Master himself.
你受到盟主的培训
Did he pass down the fleur-de-lis? Is that how you found this?
他把白色鸢尾花传给你? 所以你才找到这玩意?
And he must have sung you the riddle songs.
那他一定唱过谜歌给你听
I know some of them.
我会哼一点
Can you keep secrets?
你能保密吗?
Can you know a thing and never say it again?
你能对一件事守口如瓶吗?
And codes?
还有密码?
I imagine they lie down for you like lovers.
破解密码对你来说一定易如反掌
A Senechal. A guardian of the Grail right here in my own home.
锡安会大长老 圣杯守护者就在我家
Tell him, please. I don't know any of this.
告诉他我什么都不知道
Leigh, it's not that simple. She doesn't rem...
事情没这么简单 她不记...
Robert!
罗柏!
Do not move, woman.
不要动 女人
Cripple.
臭瘸子
Put the box on the table.
把木盒放在桌上
What, this trifle?
什么? 这玩意?
Well, perhaps we can make a financial arrangement.
也许我们可以做金钱上的交易
Put the keystone on the table.
把拱心石放在桌上
You will not succeed.
你们不会成功的
Only the worthy can unlock the stone.
只有正直的人才能打开拱心石
Rip the gate down.
把铁栅栏拉开
Well, well, my dear.
你真厉害
Sit down.
坐下来
- Are you okay? - Yeah, yeah.
- 你没事吧? - 没事
- Are you? - Yeah.
- 你呢? - 没事
Yes, well, make yourself useful, you French fool.
快来帮忙 蠢法国佬
Get something to restrain this monster.
找东西把这怪物绑起来
Above the joint.
绑在关节上方
Fortunately, a dragon most easy to slay.
幸好这只恶龙很好对付
He's wearing a cilice.
他戴着苦修带
- A what? - Well, look.
- 什么? - 你看
Inflicts pain so he can suffer as Christ suffered.
亲自体验基督受过的痛苦
Not so common these days.
这种东西不常见了
Opus Dei.
主业会
Remy, take care of this.
黑密 处理一下
Fache is Opus Dei.
法舍也是主业会会员
The policeman who's chasing us. He wears the cross in the world.
追捕我们的警察也有戴徽章
Robert.
罗柏
Well, I must say, you two are anything but dull.
你们俩的生活真是刺激
Leigh?
李伊
You want what's in this box?
你要木盒里的东西吗?
We need a way out of here.
帮助我们逃走
Well, actually...
老实说
I do have a plane.
我有一架私人喷射机
- Robert! Where do we go? - Come along.
- 罗柏 走哪里? - 跟我走
- In here. Come in. - Over here.
- 这里 进去 - 这里
Get the door. Hurry.
快开门
Over here. Over here. Sophie.
这里 苏菲
Watch out!
小心
Be careful.
(谷仓)
Come, Rem...
来吧
Shit.
该死
Easy.
开慢点
Jesus!
我的主啊
Apropos.
说的好
I can't imagine what your complaint is.
我不知道你在气什么
I'd be within my rights to shoot you and let you rot in my woods!
我大可以一枪把你打死
Put that away. We might need him.
把枪拿开 我们也许需要他
Better.
好多了
Opus Dei.
主业会
- What is it? - A conservative Catholic sect.
- 是什么? - 保守的天主教教派
Opus Dei is a prelature to the Vatican.
隶属梵蒂冈教廷
You're saying the Vatican is killing people for this box?
梵蒂冈教廷为了这个木盒杀人?
No, no, no. Not the Vatican...
不是梵蒂冈教廷或是主业会
and not Opus Dei, but we are in the middle of a war.
不过我们被卷入一场大战
And one that has been going on forever.
持续两千年的战争
On the one side stands the Priory...
一边是锡安会
and on the other an ancient group of despots...
另一边是一个古老的秘密组织
with members hidden in high-ranking positions...
成员包括教廷的高层人士
throughout the Church.
这个所谓的影子会
And this Council of Shadows tries to destroy proof of the bloodline.
想毁灭耶稣有后代的证据
And that throughout history, they seek out and kill...
他们一直在寻找
the living descendants of Jesus Christ.
并企图杀害耶稣基督的后代
- That's insane. - Is it?
- 这太扯了 - 是吗?
How many atrocities and scandals has the Catholic Church...
天主教教会在世上 已为多少暴行与丑闻
rationalized in its time? And what happens...
找过借口了?
if some persuasive scientific evidence emerges that shows...
如果有充分有力的科学根据...
that the Church's version of Christ is inaccurate?
证明教会所形塑的耶稣并不正确 那会如何?
What if the world discovers...
如果世人发现
that the greatest story ever told is actually a lie?
《圣经》全是谎言
The Vatican faces a crisis of faith unprecedented.
梵蒂冈教廷将面临空前的危机
I've got a signal now, sir. It's ringing.
收到讯号 打通了
Roger, look, I'm so sorry. I've got tired of the weather here in France...
罗杰 不好意思 我受够了法国的天气
and could you make the plane ready for...
请你准备起飞
Zurich.
飞往苏黎世
Yes. No, we love Zurich.
对 我们喜欢苏黎世
What the hell do you mean, you lost them? Collet.
你让他们逃走了?
You're the one who lost them.
是你让他们逃走了
You control every step of this investigation.
你把每个人管得死死的
You don't let anybody breathe.
不准我们随机应变
You're acting like you lost your mind.
你简直就像发疯似的
What is it with these two birds?
这两个人有什么特别?
Interpol just registered a new flight plan from Le Bourget.
布荷杰机场有架飞机准备起飞
Stay out of my way on this, Collet.
你最不要多问 科列
Did you kill Jacques Sauniere?
你杀死贾克索尼耶赫吗?
I am the messenger of God.
我是上帝的使者
Did you kill my grandfather?
是不是你杀死我祖父?
I am the messenger...
我是上帝的...
Each breath you take is a sin.
你吸的每一口气都是罪恶
No shadow will be safe again.
你在世上再也无可遁形
For you will be hunted by angels.
因为你将被天使猎杀
You believe in God?
你相信上帝吗?
Your God doesn't forgive murderers.
你的上帝不会宽恕杀人凶手
He burns them.
祂会让他们下地狱
Sophie.
苏菲
The Teacher will be pleased.
老师会很高兴
What will you do once you have the Grail?
你拿到圣杯要怎么处理?
Destroy it.
把它给毁了
The documents and the sarcophagus, of course.
我是说文献和石棺
And the heir?
他的后裔呢?
Will you exercise the final edict? Spill his blood?
你会遵守命令除掉他吗?
There will be no need.
没这个必要
Once the sarcophagus is destroyed, DNA testing will be impossible.
只要摧毁石棺 就不能做DNA检验
There is no way to prove a living bloodline.
不可能证明耶稣有后代
But if you had to...
不过如果有必要
would you do as councils have done before us?
你愿意像我们的前辈一样杀人吗?
Christ...
耶稣基督...
Christ sacrificed his life for the betterment of humanity.
耶稣基督为全人类牺牲性命
So, too, may be the fate of his seed.
这也是祂的后代的命运
Robert.
罗柏
When we land, you must go straight to your embassy.
一降落你要马上去你的大使馆
Is that so?
真的吗?
Don't you see it?
你看不出来吗?
They never wanted you.
他们要的不是你
Maybe even Fache didn't.
或许连法舍要的都不是你
It's all about this...
一切都是关于这个...
idiotic little box.
愚蠢的小盒子
That's not too flattering.
一点也不恭维
Crazy old man.
那个老疯子
Why leave me with this?
为何留下这个给我?
I should just throw it away.
我应该把它丢掉
He trusted you, Sophie.
苏菲 他相信你
A guardian of the Holy Grail.
圣杯的守护者
It sounds so stupid.
听起来好愚蠢
It's quite an honor, if you think about it...
若你想想看 并认真看待它的话
and take it seriously.
这真是项荣誉
He took it seriously enough to get himself killed.
他认真到连命都没了
Not him. You.
不是他 是你
He was the only family I knew.
他是我唯一的家人
And maybe I didn't know him at all.
或许我从来不了解他
I'm his marionette, Robert.
罗柏 我是他的人偶
Like a girl again, just with no gift at the end.
又像个小女孩了 只是最后没有礼物
But you've done enough.
但你做得已经够多了
I don't know why Sauniere picked me to help you, Sophie.
苏菲 我不知索尼耶赫 为何找我帮你
But I won't leave you alone in all this.
但我不会丢下你不管的
Two marionettes, then.
那就是两个人偶了
Maybe this is why he chose you.
或许正是这样 他才选了你
Because you will stay.
因为你会留下
I need the flight plan.
我要看飞航行程表
Ten minutes.
十分钟
I asked you to get it for me.
我叫你拿给我看
I'm on break.
我正在休息
Come back in 10 minutes.
十分钟后再来
My nose! My nose!
我的鼻子!
The flight plan, please.
请把飞航行程表给我
You asshole!
王八蛋!
It's not "cross."
不是"十字架"
"Spear"?
是"矛"吗?
What happened to her?
她发生什么事?
No one knows.
没有人知道
Mary Magdalene lived out her days in hiding.
抹大拉的马利亚终生躲藏
And the zealots pursued her still...
连死后都有人想找到她的石棺
even in death, trying to destroy proof of her existence.
企图摧毁她存在的证据
But she always had her Knights.
幸好她有圣殿骑士团
Brave men sworn to defend her.
他们誓死保护她
You see, to worship before her sarcophagus...
跪在她的石棺前面
to kneel before the bones of Mary Magdalene...
祭拜她的遗骨
was to remember all those who were robbed of their power...
就是纪念所有受到压迫...
who were oppressed.
被剥夺权利的人们
Ultimately, the Priory hid her remains and the proof of her bloodline...
她的遗骨和血脉证据被藏起来
until most believed her sarcophagus...
直到世人相信她的石棺
the Holy Grail...
也就是圣杯
was finally lost in time.
从此再也不会出现
What are you doing?
你在干嘛?
At the chateau, you said, "It hides beneath the Rose."
你说"它藏在玫瑰标志下方"
No, no, no. Do be careful.
小心点
In Latin, Sub roSa. Literal translation...
拉丁文的直译是...
"Beneath the rose."
"玫瑰之下"
We need a mirror.
我们需要一面镜子
Backwards. In the style of Leonardo himself.
倒写文字 达芬奇的习惯
Thank you.
谢谢你
In London lies a knight a Pope interred
伦敦骑士身后为教宗所埋葬
His labor's fruit a Holy wrath incurred
一生功绩徒惹圣座愤怒难当
You seek the orb that ought be on his tomb
欲觅之球原应栖于英雄墓上
It speaks of Rosy flesh and seeded womb
瑰红肌夫与受孕子宫细思量
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred"?
"伦敦骑士身后为教宗所埋葬"?
A knight whose funeral was presided over by the Pope.
教宗为一名骑士主持葬礼
Of course, the Priory knights were not just any knights.
没错 锡安会骑士非比寻常
Templars.
他们是圣殿骑士
And there's just one place to bury a Templar knight in London.
伦敦只有一个地方安葬圣殿骑士
Temple Church.
圣殿教堂
Temple Church. If you'll excuse me, my dear...
没错 恕我失陪
Roger and I must discuss a change in flight plan.
我得请罗杰改变飞航行程表
Leigh.
李伊
Harboring and transporting fugitives?
窝藏并协助逃犯
You are already implicated enough.
你卷入的麻烦够多了
You and I, Robert, have observed history.
我和你一生都在研究历史
Time has been our glass.
只能透过史料了解历史
We are in history now. Living it.
现在我们活在历史中
Making it.
创造历史
"Lmplicated"?
卷入麻烦?
I am on a Grail quest.
我正在寻找圣杯
Forgive me, Robert...
我就这么说吧
but you two may well have given this old man...
你们两个人给了这个老人
the greatest night of his life.
这一生中最美好的一晚
Thank you.
谢谢你
He's going to want more money.
他一定会要更多钱
I suppose this is a new technique for investigations.
我猜你用的是全新的办案手法
I've lost them. They flew to Switzerland.
我把他们追丢了 他们飞到瑞士
No extradition.
瑞士没有引渡条约
The controller filed charges. Ari was on dispatch. He called me.
那名管制员提出告诉 总部打电话告诉我了
What's going on, Bezu?
到底是怎么回事?
You know that I am Opus Dei?
你知道我是主业会会员?
Yes.
没错
A bishop of my order called me.
我的教区主教打电话给我
He said a killer came to him in confession.
他说一名凶手向他告解
His name was Robert Langdon.
他的名字是罗柏兰登
He said I couldn't imagine the evil in this man's heart.
他说这个人的内心邪恶到极点
That he would keep killing.
他会继续杀人
He said I had to stop him.
而我必须阻止他
The bishop broke his vows to tell me this.
主教违背誓言告诉我这件事
He charged me to stop Robert Langdon.
他要我负责阻止罗柏兰登
Tell me, Collet, who have I failed?
科列 告诉我 我辜负了谁的期望?
The bishop?
那名主教吗?
God himself?
或是上帝?
They've changed their flight plan to London.
他们更改飞航行程表前往伦敦了
Go on, Fache. I'll take care of the controller.
去吧 法舍 我来看住塔台
Maybe he needs a few extra euros.
他也许会多要一些钱
Just tell me next time.
但下次要先知会我一声
I have them, tower. Relay Hawker to land and hold on tarmac.
塔台 我看到飞机了 通知机长降落之后停在跑道
- Secure the area! - Wider!
- 封锁整座机场 - 扩大封锁线
- Armed police! - You two, round the back!
- 警察! - 你们绕到后面
Armed police! Put your hands in the air!
警察 把手举起来!
- Three men up! - Ready!
- 准备抓人! - 预备!
Put your hands in the air! Do it now!
把手举起来 快点!
I'm afraid that's easier said than done in my case.
这对我来说没这么容易
Oh, good morning.
早安
Did that old cannabis charge finally catch up with me?
我夹带大麻的事终于曝光了?
Sir, the French police say you're transporting fugitives...
法国警方指控你窝藏逃犯
and you may have a hostage onboard.
机上也可能有一名人质
I'm to take you all into custody.
我要把你们都抓起来
Sadly, I have an important medical appointment which I can't miss.
我预约了要去看病 不能不去
I'll fetch the car, sir.
我去把车子开来
This is serious, sir. The French police are on their way. Stop!
事态严重 法国警方正赶来 站住
Inspector, I can't afford the time to indulge your games.
探长 我没时间陪你玩游戏
I'm late and I'm leaving.
我已经迟到了 我要走了
If it's so important for you to stop us...
你想阻止我们
then you're just going to have to shoot us.
就射杀我们吧
You can start with him.
先从他下手
Search the plane.
给我上飞机搜
All right.
好吧
I could run them over.
我可以开车撞倒他们
Bad tip.
情报有误
Let him go.
让他们走吧
The French cannot be trusted.
千万不能相信法国佬
Everyone comfy?
大伙儿都舒服吗?
Biscuits?
来块饼干?
They didn't notice anything?
他们什么也没看到?
Well, people rarely notice things right in front of their eyes, don't you find?
大家都对眼前的事情视若无睹
Do you have the bonds, bishop?
你拿到债券了吗?
Yes, I do, Teacher.
拿到了 老师
I have chosen an Opus Dei residence for the exchange.
我选择在主业会宿舍进行交易
I am honored.
这是我的荣幸
By the time you get to London, I will have the Grail.
等你到了伦敦 我就会把圣杯拿到手
- I take it the news is good, then. - I fly to London.
- 我猜是有好新闻吧 - 我要飞去伦敦
The Teacher is waiting for me there.
老师在那里等我
He has chosen a house of Opus Dei to make the exchange.
他选择主业会的一个宿舍 做交换地点
Mere currency for the location of the Grail.
用钱就能买到圣杯地点
Imagine it.
想像一下
Remember, if we are discovered by the Vatican, we are excommunicated.
记住 如果被梵蒂冈发现 我们都会被逐出教会
- So should anything go wrong... - Yes, I know, I know.
- 要是出了什么差错... - 我知道
This council does not exist.
影子会并不存在
As it never has.
从来就不存在
Old friend. Heaven protect you.
老友 天主会保佑你
Keep an eye out for the police.
注意看有没有警察
I must say, Robert, I'm quite impressed...
罗柏 我真的很佩服你
by the way you withstood my little aeroplane.
坐在小小的飞机上没被吓死
Did he never tell you?
他没告诉你吗?
When he was a boy, young Robert fell into a well.
罗柏小时候曾经掉进一口水井
How old were you?
当时你几岁?
Seven.
七岁
Treading water all night long, screaming his lungs out...
他整晚踢着井水
to the echoes screaming back.
只听见自己求救声的回音
When they found him, he was nearly catatonic.
他被发现时几乎变成植物人
Help!
救命啊!
It was a long time ago.
那是很久以前的事了
Oh, now, now, Robert.
别这么说 罗柏
You above all people shouldn't be one to dismiss the influence of the past.
你应该最清楚 过去对现在的影响有多大
Temple Church. I always forget it's right here.
圣殿教堂 我总忘记它就在这里
Built 1185 and modern London just sprang up right around it.
于1185年建造后 现代伦敦便围绕着它建立
Tell me, why has the Priory kept the Grail location secret all these years?
告诉我 锡安会为何一直保守圣杯秘密?
I don't know.
我不知道
Some say the Priory wait for the heir to reveal himself...
有人说锡安会等待耶稣后裔现身
which is especially odd...
这一点非常奇怪
since legend suggests he may not know his own true identity.
因为在传说中他不知道自己的身份
Hello?
有人吗?
Why do they make them so scary?
教堂为什么都这么可怕?
Oh, it's cold.
好冷哦
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred."
"伦敦骑士身后为教宗所埋葬"
So which tomb has an orb?
哪一座坟墓上面有圆球?
Those knights with their legs crossed...
这些武士两腿交叉
means they'd been to the Holy Land.
代表他们已去过圣土
Two wear tunics over their armor...
有两个的盔甲外面套着及膝外袍
and two have full-length robes.
其中三个穿着全身长袍
Two are grasping swords.
另外两个手握宝剑
And one... Two are praying.
一个... 两个在祈祷
This one has his arms at his sides.
这一个双手垂在两侧
Oh, and this poor fellow has almost disappeared entirely.
这个可怜的家伙几乎全毁
I don't see any orb that ought be on a tomb.
我没看到有缺了圆球的坟墓
"Ought be on his tomb." Are we looking for a missing orb?
缺了圆球的坟墓 我们在找遗失的圆球吗?
Maybe.
也许吧
These aren't tombs.
这些不是坟墓
- What? Yes, of course they are. - No.
- 什么? 当然是了 - 不
- They're effigies. - What?
- 这些是雕像 - 什么?
Not tombs. There's no bodies here.
不是坟墓 下面没有遗骸
This place is wrong.
这个地方不对劲
Can we go now? We should go.
可以走了吗? 我们该走了
Sophie! No!
苏菲! 不!
Where is the keystone?
拱心石在哪里?
Do not test me!
不要逼我下手
- Let her go! - Don't hurt her.
- 放开她 - 不准伤害她
Give me the keystone! Give it to me!
把拱心石给我 把东西给我!
Here! Here! Here it is! Here it is.
东西在我这里!
Just let her go, and you and I can... We'll come to some agreement.
让她走 我们两个来解决这件事
Remy.
黑密
Remy. No, no, no. No, put it away.
黑密 不 把枪放下
Put it away. They're too close together. You don't have a clear shot.
他们靠得太近 你射不到目标
- Yes, I do. - What do you think you're doing?
- 我射得到 - 住手 你在做什么?
Thank you, professor. For a moment, this was getting complicated.
谢谢你 教授 事情差点就被搞砸
Oh, this is absurd. Oh, for God's sake, man!
这太荒谬了 别这么做
That was satisfying.
那真是痛快
I'm glad this bullshit is over.
很高兴事情都解决了
Throw Teabing in the trunk.
把提宝塞进后车厢
What?
什么?
Here. You okay?
来 你没事吧?
Sorry.
抱歉了
I don't think he's following.
他没有追上来
They won't kill Leigh until they find the Grail.
他们没找到圣杯不会杀死李伊
- So we have to find it before they do. - I have to get to a library, fast.
- 我们要赶在他们前面找到它 - 我得尽快找到一间图书馆
Lieutenant!
警官
One flag off the prints.
指纹比对有结果了
Remy Legaludec.
黑密勒加鲁德
Petty theft.
是个小罪犯
Skipped out on a hospital bill for a tracheotomy.
他没付气管切开术的手术费
Peanut allergy.
而且对花生过敏
Like Marie.
和玛丽一样
This way. Marie?
那边走 玛丽是谁?
My daughter.
我女儿
Over here.
这里
Where?
走哪边?
Up there.
那边上去
What's all that?
那些是什么?
Very advanced surveillance.
非常先进的监控系统
It's a listening post.
这是监听站
(杰克索尼耶赫)
(爱德华德鲁谢)
Get me Fache.
帮我打电话给法舍
Four of these names are the men killed last night.
昨晚的四个受害者都在里头
He once whined to me about the wasted space of so large a trunk.
他曾经抱怨后车厢太大浪费空间
Let's see if he complains so now.
看他现在还敢不敢抱怨
Are you the Teacher?
你是老师吗?
I am.
是的
Superbly done. You've been of great service.
这件事做得很好 你帮了很大的忙
The cryptex has yet to be opened. I can still serve.
藏密筒没打开 我还可以帮忙
You've done enough.
你做的够多了
We cannot let ego deter us from our goal.
我们不能为自己偏离原来的目标
I understand.
我了解
Good.
很好
Wait here, at this house of Opus Dei, and you will be rewarded.
在这间主业会宿舍等待 你将得到奖赏
I will dispose of the old man.
我会处理那个老头子
Bless you, Silas.
愿主祝福你 西拉
Teacher.
老师
Christ be with you.
愿主与你同在
We're at least a half-hour to Chelsea Library.
要花半小时才能到却尔希图书馆
If we're gonna help Leigh, that's too long.
这样来不及救李伊
(罗浮宫谋杀案)
Where you going?
你要去哪里?
Getting you a library card.
帮你弄一张图书证
Excuse me. May I sit next to you?
我能坐这儿吗?
- Yeah, sure. - Thank you.
- 可以啊 - 谢谢
That's great.
太好了
Didn't say you had a boyfriend.
你没说你有男友
Thanks.
谢了
Let's see if we can access the database on this.
我看能不能进入资料库
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred."
"伦敦骑士身后为教宗所埋葬"
Compounding keywords:
搜寻关键字串
Knight, Pope, Grail.
骑士 教宗 圣杯
Your precious treasure was almost lost, and with it, my fortune.
你差点失去你的宝物 我的钱也差点拿不到手
Can you believe how well I did?
我的演技很好 对吧?
I even convinced the monk.
连那个隐修士都被我骗了
I should be in theater.
我应该去演戏的
A toast to our success, Teacher. The end of the journey is near.
为我们的成功干杯 老师 已经接近终点了
Your identity shall go with me to the grave.
你的身份会跟着我进坟墓
There's your problem, mate. It's your basic linguistic coincidence.
问题就出在这里 同样的拼法有不同的意思
See, keywords keep coming up with the writings...
搜寻"教宗"这个关键字
of some bloke named Alexander Pope.
却一直出现亚历山大波普的名字
"A. Pope."
"A. Pope"
Your grandfather was a genius.
你祖父真是个天才
Come on.
走吧
Emergency. Which service do you require?
紧急报案中心 有什么事?
I know the location of two murderers wanted by French police.
我知道法国警方的通缉犯在哪里
We've just had a 999 call.
我们接到报案电话
Triangulation leads back to Docklands.
查出是从码头区打来的
Caller was male. Claimed your two murderers...
对方是男性 宣称两名杀人犯
are hiding at an Opus Dei house.
藏匿在主业会宿舍
The knight we're looking for is Sir Isaac Newton.
我们要找的骑士是牛顿爵士
His life's work produced new sciences that incurred the wrath of the Church.
他研究的新科学理论激怒教会
Gravity, for God sakes.
万有引力 太过份了
And if you choose to believe...
如果你选择相信的话...
he was also a Grand Master of the Priory as well.
他也曾经是锡安会的盟主
But if he offended the Catholic Church...
要是他激怒天主教教会
the Pope would be the last person to preside over his funeral.
教宗不可能主持他的葬礼
Well, that's where I got it wrong.
我误解这句谜语的意思
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred."
"伦敦骑士身后为教宗所埋葬"
Sir Isaac Newton's funeral was presided over...
牛顿爵士的葬礼由他的好友...
by his good friend, his colleague, Alexander Pope.
也是他的同事亚历山大波普主持
A. Pope. His first initial. How did I miss that?
"A. Pope"A是名字缩写 我竟然没想到
Here.
这里
Yes. Isaac Newton's tomb.
艾萨克牛顿的坟墓
An orb.
一个圆球
Yes. Which one? It's not possible to tell if a particular orb is missing.
到底是哪一个? 看不出缺了哪一个圆球
"An orb with Rosy flesh and seeded womb."
"瑰红肌夫与受孕子宫细思量"
Solar system. The planets. Constellations. Signs of the zodiac.
太阳系 行星... 星座 黄道十二宫各星座
See, our moon is missing.
地球的月球不见了
The moons of Saturn and Jupiter. They're not here.
也没有土星和木星的月球
Eyes of the cherubs themselves?
是双翼童子的眼球吗?
Robert. These tracks.
罗柏 这些足印
Look at the cane marks in the dust.
地上有拐杖踩过的痕迹
Teabing was here.
提宝来过这里
He was alone.
只有他一个人
When the two of you arrived at my home as you did...
当你们两个人深夜来到我家
others might call it God's will.
有人会说那是上帝的旨意
I believed that if I had the cryptex...
我本来相信只要拿到藏密筒
I could solve the riddle alone.
我就能一个人解开谜语
But I was unworthy.
但是我不够资格
But you...
不过你...
You have a reason to be here.
你才有资格
You're the last remaining guardian of the Grail.
你是圣杯最后一位守护者
Your grandfather and the other Senechaux...
你祖父和其他大长老
would not have lied with dying breath...
必须确保这秘密不曝光
unless they knew their secret was preserved.
不然就会死不瞑目
How could you know Sauniere's last words?
你怎么会知道索尼耶赫的遗言?
Leigh.
李伊
Grail quests require sacrifice.
寻找圣杯必须牺牲人命
You are a murderer.
你是杀人凶手
No. No. Robert, tell her.
不 罗柏 告诉她
When history is written, murderers are heroes.
赢家的历史将杀人凶手变成英雄
You self-righteous bastard!
你这自以为是的混球
We need to just walk away.
我们只想离开
No, don't. Don't.
不行 站住
I'll do what I have to now.
我什么事都做得出来
Anything.
包括杀人
Do you understand?
你们明白吗?
So now...
现在...
can't we all be friends again?
让我们和和气气当朋友吧
This way.
这里
I'm going to put this gun down. I only want you both to listen.
我要先把枪放下 你们最好乖乖听我说
I'm listening now.
我正在听
For 2000 years...
两千年来
the Church has rained oppression and atrocity upon mankind...
教会以高压手段迫害全人类
crushed passion and idea alike, all in the name of their walking God.
镇压人类的热情与思想 全都是以主耶稣基督之名
Proof of Jesus' mortality can bring an end to all that suffering...
证明耶稣是凡人能终结人类苦难
drive this church of lies to its knees.
逼迫建立在谎言上的教会臣服
Armed police!
警察!
Drop your weapon!
把枪放下!
Stop, Silas!
住手 西拉
We are betrayed, my son.
我们遭到背叛了 孩子
The living heir must be revealed.
一定要揭露耶稣后代的身份
Jesus must be shown for what he was.
让世人知道耶稣的真相
Not miraculous, simply man.
他不是神 而是凡人
I'm sorry.
很遗憾
Armed police!
警察!
Drop your weapon! Drop it! Drop it!
把枪放下! 快放下!
Put it down now! Put it down!
把枪放下!
I am a ghost.
我是个幽魂
The dark con can be exposed.
我可以揭发阴暗的骗局
Mankind can finally be set free, and we can do it, Robert.
让人类终于重获自由 我们办得到 罗柏
The three of us.
我们三个人
How is Silas?
西拉怎么样?
Is he...? Is he alive?
他... 还活着吗?
The monk?
那个隐修士?
Bishop, how would you know this killer's name?
你怎么会知道凶手的名字?
Get me out of here, Fache.
把我带走 法舍
Wait.
等等
Langdon never came to you in confession, did he?
兰登没去向你告解 对吧?
One of your followers called you about the crime-scene photos.
你说服我把犯罪现场照片给你看
I cannot be implicated here. There are still important works to be done.
我不能被牵涉进去 我还有很多重要的事要做
You used me.
你利用了我
God uses us all.
上帝利用了我们
Help me, Fache.
帮助我 法舍
Take him.
把他带走吧
- Did you get his cell phone? - Yes, sir.
- 你拿到他的手机吗? - 拿到了
I'm going to need a trace.
请你追踪一通电话
Your Silas is dead.
你的西拉死了
The Priory's sacred charge...
锡安会的神圣使命就是
was to reveal the heir at the dawn of the new millennium.
在千禧年揭露耶稣后代的身份
The millennium came and went and the living heir remained hidden.
千禧年已经过去了 耶稣后代的身份仍是秘密
The Priory failed in their sacred charge.
锡安会没有完成它的神圣使命
So, what choice did I have?
我有什么其它的选择?
I sought out the enemy.
我主动去找敌人
I persuaded them, the Council of Shadows, that I was an ally.
说服他们 也就是影子会 我是他们的盟友
I even asked them for money so they would never suspect me.
我甚至向他们要钱以免被怀疑
Rector, I made them call me.
我要他们叫我"指导者"
"Teacher."
就是"老师"
- Why don't you and I... - No.
- 你和我不如... - 不
Robert, no words. On your knees.
不要说话 跪下来
Do it.
快点
No, I mean it. Down.
我是说真的 快跪下
Not you. No, my dear, you...
你不用 亲爱的
You're my miracle, Sophie.
你是我的奇迹 苏菲
You're the guardian of the Grail.
你是圣杯守护者
All the oppression of the poor and the powerless...
世上每一个受到迫害的弱者
of those of different skin, of women.
不同夫色的种族和女性
You can put an end to all that.
你可以阻止这一切的恶行
You must explode the truth onto the world.
向世人揭开这个惊人的秘密
It's your duty.
这是你的使命
You know the answer to this riddle.
你知道这个谜语的解答
Open the cryptex...
打开藏密筒
and I'll put down the gun.
我就把枪放下
I have no idea how.
我不晓得该怎么打开
I don't know the code.
我不知道密码
And even if I did, I wouldn't tell you.
就算知道也不会告诉你
Like your grandfather, then.
那你就跟你祖父一样
Willing to die for your secret.
宁死都要保守秘密
But by the way you've been looking at your hero...
既然你这么关心你的英雄
I wonder, would you let him die for you?
不知道你愿不愿意让他为你死?
Open it, Sophie, to save his life.
打开来才能救他一命
- Leigh, you can't just... - Open the cryptex.
- 李伊 你不能... - 打开藏密筒
I don't know how.
我不知道怎么打开
Open it or he dies.
你不打开他就死
- I swear, I don't know. - Do it! Do it!
- 我发誓我不会 - 快点!
- Stop it! - I don't know!
- 别逼她! - 我不知道
Stop it!
别逼她!
She can't do it, Leigh.
她办不到
But give me a moment.
不过给我一点时间
Robert.
罗柏
What are you doing?
你在干嘛?
Please.
求求你
I'm sorry.
很遗憾
No!
不!
No, Robert!
不 罗柏
No!
不!
No.
不
Oh, the map. It's ruined.
地图被毁了
The map is ruined.
The Grail.
圣杯...
It's lost.
永远找不到了
The Grail is gone.
永远找不到圣杯了
Only the worthy find the Grail, Leigh.
只有正直的人才能找到圣杯
You taught me that.
这是你自己说的
Armed police!
警察!
Drop it! Drop your weapon!
把枪放下!
Put the gun down.
把枪放下
That one. The old man.
那一个 老头子
You're under arrest!
你被捕了
You do not have to say anything, but it may harm your defense...
你什么都不必说
if you do not mention, when questioned...
你若有所隐瞒
something which you later rely on in court.
将对你不利
Anything you do say will be given in evidence.
你说的一切将成为呈堂证供
I'll have some questions for you.
我要好好问你的话
Big crowd out there now.
外面聚集了大批人潮
Thank you for your statements. You are free to go, of course.
谢谢你们的供词 当然 你们可以走了
I'm sorry. You thought he was your friend, no?
我很遗憾 你以为他是你的朋友吧?
It wasn't only us, was it?
不只是我们吧?
He used you too.
他也利用了你
Leave us, please.
请离开
I should have been smarter.
我应该聪明一点的
I acted on faith, I suppose.
我猜我是靠信念行动
I'm sorry.
很遗憾
How many?
有几个人?
Your grandfather, the other three, maybe more.
你的祖父 其他三个人 或许还有
The monk was given to Teabing as a gift, it seems.
隐修士似乎被送给提宝作礼物
To do as he asked.
为他效劳
Teabing killed the servant himself, you know.
提宝亲手杀了仆人 你知道
- Remy? - Yes.
- 是黑密? - 对
By poison.
是毒杀
How much of it have you been able to figure out?
你解开了其中多少?
Some. Not enough for it to make sense.
一部份 还无法完全了解
It won't ever make sense.
它永远无法被了解
I'm sorry.
很遗憾
He forgot everything we've learned.
他忘了我们所学的一切
Everything we teach.
我们所教的一切
It's why we study history.
但这是学习历史的理由
So we'll stop killing each other.
让我们不再自相残杀
Robert! Robert! Robert! How could you do it?
罗柏 你怎么能这么做?
How could you? Robert!
你怎么能毁了它?
To destroy our hope of freedom.
你毁了我们重获自由的希望
To deny every pilgrim the chance to kneel at the tomb of the Magdalene.
剥夺每一个朝圣者 在抹大拉墓前跪拜的机会
How could you?
你怎么能毁了它?
You couldn't! You solved it.
你成功了 你解开密码
You took the scroll out before it broke!
你先把莎草纸拿出来才打破它
You solved it. Oh, you'll find it, Robert. You'll find it. You know what to do.
你破解了密码 你会找到它 你知道该怎么做
You'll find the Grail, you'll kneel before her...
找到圣杯 跪在她面前
and you'll set her free upon the world!
在世人面前让她重获自由
That man there, he's got the map to the Holy Grail!
那个人拿到寻找圣杯的地图
There was every orb conceivable on that tomb except one:
那座墓碑上有各种圆球 除了一个以外
The orb which fell from the heavens and inspired Newton's life's work.
从天上掉下来的圆球 启发牛顿毕生研究的灵感
Work that incurred the wrath of the Church until his dying day.
直到他死为止都受到教会迫害
A-P-P-L-E.
A-P-P-L-E
Apple.
苹果
The Holy Grail 'neath ancient Roslin waits
古老罗丝林下圣杯静待
The blade and chalice guarding o'er her gates
刀刃与圣爵守护伊门宅
Adorned in masters' loving art, she lies
献大师杰作 相伴入梦
She rests at last beneath the starry skies
她终可安息 仰对星空
I think I know where she's gone.
我知道她去了哪里
I think the Grail has gone home.
圣杯回家了
Built by the Templars themselves. Named for the original Rose Line.
圣殿骑士团亲自建造 以最古老的玫瑰线命名
Rosslyn Chapel.
罗丝林礼拜堂
So this is it.
就是这里了
The gift at the end.
礼物就藏在这里
"The Holy Grail 'neath ancient Roslin waits."
"古老罗丝林下圣杯静待"
You never told me the joke Sauniere made of you.
你没告诉我索尼耶赫说你的笑话
What was it?
什么笑话?
He called me a flatfoot.
他说我是一个条子
A beat cop of history.
历史的推理员
Oh, a dumb policeman...
一个笨警察
who just does his job day after day, of history.
只会日复一日埋首在史料堆中
You know, his father was one. A policeman.
他的父亲是一名警察
Sauniere said he was the most honorable man he had ever known.
他说他父亲是他见过最正直的人
We are who we protect, I think.
我们要保护的是我们这些凡人
What we stand up for.
以及我们扞卫的理念
Jewish...
犹太教星星
Christian, Egyptian...
基督教十字架 古埃及图腾
Masonic, pagan...
共济会标志 异教符号
Templar crosses...
圣殿骑士团正十字
pyramids.
金字塔
I think I've been here before.
我想... 我来过这里
Sophie.
苏菲
A very long time ago.
很久很久以前
Come along, Sophie.
来吧 苏菲
Sophie.
苏菲
Over here.
这里
"The blade and chalice guarding o'er her gates."
"刀刃与圣爵守护伊门宅"
Pagan symbols for male and female.
男性与女性的异教符号
Fused as one.
合而为一
As the pagans would have wanted.
完全符合异教徒的思想
We're about to close, I'm afraid.
礼拜堂就快关门了
We're just gonna be a moment.
我们只要一下子
(十三世纪圣殿武士团)
(恐怖之王)
Robert.
罗柏
I've never seen that before.
我从没看过它
The style is...
这种风格...
It's unmistakable.
显而易见
These could have been painted by Leonardo da Vinci.
这些只可能是达芬奇所作
"Adorned in masters' loving art, she lies."
"献大师杰作 相伴入梦"
"She rests at last beneath the starry skies."
"她终可安息 仰对星空"
The fleur-de-lis.
白色鸢尾花
She was here.
她曾经在这里
Her sarcophagus.
她的石棺
Mary Magdalene.
抹大拉的马利亚
The Holy Grail herself.
圣杯本身
She was here.
她曾经在这里
With modern DNA testing, those bones...
若有现代DNA测验 这些骨骸
could have shown definitive proof of a bloodline.
可能提供确实的血缘证据
Where did she go?
她去了哪里?
Did the Church finally get her?
教会最后找到她了吗?
This is incredible. Look at this.
太不可思议了 你看
Look at this. These records go back thousands of years.
你看看 这些文献有一 两千年历史
They date back to the death of Christ.
最早能追溯到耶稣去世的年代
Good God, could these really be the Grail documents?
这些真的是圣杯文献吗?
What did he want from us? To find her sarcophagus?
他到底要我们做什么? 找到她的石棺?
How was I ever supposed to figure all this out?
我该怎么理出个头绪?
When you and your grandfather fought...
你和你祖父是为了...
was it something about your past?
你的过去而闹翻的吗?
How could you know that?
你怎么会知道?
About how your parents died?
关于你父母的死因?
Sophie?
苏菲?
It was during primary school.
当时我还在念小学
I was in his library.
我到他的书房
Doing research.
偷翻资料
I was trying to find out about my family.
我想知道关于我家人的事
Sophie, where are you, princess?
苏菲公主 你在哪里?
I wanted to know about them.
我想多了解我的家人
But I couldn't find any records.
可是却找不到任何资料
Not of their death...
没有关于他们的死因...
not of the accident.
或是那场车祸的资料
I'd asked him for as long as I could remember...
我有记忆以来就一直追问他
but he would never tell me.
但是他总是不肯说
I told you, no.
我叫你不要问
But why can't I?
为什么?
He stood over me...
他挡住我
and he wouldn't let me leave.
不让我出去
They're dead. Dead and buried.
他们已经死了
Never look for them, Sophie.
永远不要追查他们的事
Promise me.
答应我
Swear it!
发誓!
Swear it to me!
向我发誓!
I kept my promise.
我信守承诺
The next week he sent me to boarding school.
一星期后他就送我到寄宿学校
One weekend I came home unexpectedly.
有一个周末我提早回家
And what I saw my grandfather doing...
看到我祖父在进行...
Some ritual.
某种仪式
I was so frightened.
我被吓坏了
We hardly ever spoke again.
我们后来就很少联络
Do you have any memories of your grandfather before the accident?
你有对祖父的记忆吗? 在那场车祸之前?
Before your parents were killed?
在你父母双亡之前?
Yeah. No. I don't know.
有 没有 我不知道
Why?
为什么?
Because I don't think he was your grandfather.
因为他并不是你的祖父
These are my parents.
他们是我的父母
My brother.
我哥哥
And this is you, isn't it?
这是你 对吧?
The paper says the entire family was killed.
报上说全家都死于车祸
The mother, the father, the boy, 6...
包括母亲 父亲 六岁的儿子
and the girl, 4.
和四岁的女儿
But your name was never Sauniere. It's Saint-Clair.
你的姓氏并不是索尼耶赫 而是圣克莱赫
It's one of the oldest families in France.
法国历史最悠久的家族之一
It's from a line of the Merovingian kings.
墨洛温王室的直系后裔
Royal blood.
王室之血
I was so wrong.
我错得太离谱了
Sauniere didn't want you to help guard the secret of the Holy Grail.
索尼耶赫不是要你守护圣杯的秘密
Sophie...
苏菲
you are the secret.
你就是那个秘密
You survived the accident.
你并没有死于车祸
If it even was an accident.
也许那根本不是车祸
The Priory found out.
锡安会发现这件事
Somehow they concealed the fact that you were alive.
他们设法隐瞒你没死的消息
They hid you with the Grand Master himself...
然后把你藏在盟主的家中
who raised you as his own.
他把你当孙女抚养长大
According to all of this...
根据这些文献
Princess Sophie...
苏菲公主
you are the heir.
你就是后裔
The end of the bloodline.
继承了那条血脉
You are the last living descendent...
你是耶稣基督...
of Jesus Christ.
最后一名后代
What is this?
这是怎么回事?
Sophie?
苏菲?
Who are you?
你到底是谁?
There have been many names.
我们有很多不同的名称
The keepers.
守护者
Guardians.
保护者
The Priory of Sion.
锡安会
But to you, Sophie, we are friends of the man who raised you:
但是对你来说 我们是你的抚养人的朋友
Jacques Sauniere.
贾克索尼耶赫
He would have wanted you to know that he loved you very much.
他一定很想让你知道他有多爱你
And that the Priory are here to protect you now...
锡安会一直会在这里保护你
as they have always protected our family.
就像他们一直保护我们家族一样
I gave you up once...
我曾经把你交给别人抚养
knowing I might never see you again.
知道我可能永远再也见不到你
I'm your grandmother, Sophie.
我是你的亲生祖母
I have prayed for this moment for a very long time.
长久以来我都在祈祷这一刻来临
Welcome home, child.
欢迎回家 孩子
Hey.
嘿
No more strings.
不再有操纵了
His last breath to keep me safe.
是他保护我的最后一口气
She has some things she wants to tell me.
她有一些事情要告诉我
About my family.
关于我的家族
What will you do?
你要怎么做?
The legend will be revealed when the heir reveals himself.
耶稣后代现身 "他"就会揭露真相
They just got the pronoun wrong.
他们只是把代名词搞错了
She said when Sauniere died...
她说索尼耶赫死后
he took the location of Mary's sarcophagus with him.
就把马利亚石棺的下落带进坟墓
So there's no way to empirically prove that I am related to her.
没人能证明我和她有血缘关系
What would you do, Robert?
换作你会怎么做?
Okay, maybe there is no proof. Maybe the Grail is lost forever.
也许没有任何证据 也许永远找不到圣杯
But, Sophie, the only thing that matters is what you believe.
但是重要的是你相信什么
History shows us Jesus was an extraordinary man...
根据历史 耶稣是一位伟人
a human inspiration. That's it.
启发了人心 就这样
That's all the evidence has ever proved.
这是唯一能证明的事实
But...
不过...
when I was a boy...
我小时候
When I was down in that well Teabing told you about...
当我掉进提宝跟你说的水井
I thought I was going to die, Sophie.
我以为我死定了
What I did...
我唯一能做的是...
I prayed.
祈祷
I prayed to Jesus to keep me alive...
我向耶稣祈祷 让我活下去
so I could see my parents again...
好让我能再看到父母
so I could go to school again...
再去上学
so I could play with my dog.
和我的小狗玩
Sometimes I wonder if I wasn't alone down there.
那时候我怀疑耶稣当时与我同在
Why does it have to be human or divine?
他是人或神为什么这么重要?
Maybe human is divine.
也许人就是神
Why couldn't Jesus have been a father...
耶稣为什么不能当父亲...
and still been capable of all those miracles?
同时也做出那些奇迹?
Like turning water into wine?
像是把清水变成葡萄酒?
Well, who knows? His blood is your blood.
谁晓得? 你继承了他的血脉
Maybe that junkie in the park will never touch a drug again.
也许公园那个毒虫从此就戒毒
Maybe you healed my phobia with your hands.
也许你治愈了我的幽闭恐惧症
And maybe you're a knight on a Grail quest.
也许你是寻找圣杯的骑士
Well, here's the question:
唯一的问题是
A living descendent of Jesus Christ...
耶稣基督活生生的后代...
would she destroy faith?
她会摧毁基督教信仰?
Or would she renew it?
或是加强这个信仰?
So again I say, what matters is what you believe.
我再强调这全要看你相信什么
Thank you.
谢谢你
For bringing me here.
把我带到这里
For letting him choose you...
让他选择你
Sir Robert.
罗柏爵士
You take care.
你要好好保重
Yes.
没错
Hey.
嘿
Nope.
不行
Maybe I'll do better with the wine.
也许葡萄酒那招会比较有用
Godspeed.
愿主祝福你
(《神圣女性的符号》)
Bloodline.
血痕
Rose Line.
玫瑰线
(玫瑰线)
"Hides beneath the Rose."
藏在玫瑰标志之下
(阿拉戈)
"The Holy Grail 'neath ancient Roslin waits.
"古老罗丝林下圣杯静待"
Adorned in masters' loving art, she lies.
"献大师杰作 相伴入梦"
The blade and chalice guarding o'er her gates.
"刀刃与圣爵守护伊门宅"
She rests at last beneath starry skies."
"她终可安息 仰对星空"